<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A geographicall and anthologicall description of all the empires and kingdomes, both of continent and ilands in this terrestriall globe Relating their scituations, manners, customes, prouinces, and gouernements.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Robert, 1588-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852980</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 939:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A geographicall and anthologicall description of all the empires and kingdomes, both of continent and ilands in this terrestriall globe Relating their scituations, manners, customes, prouinces, and gouernements.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Robert, 1588-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 67, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] C[otes] for Simon VVaterson, dwelling at the signe of the Crowne in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rob. Stafforde.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A geographicall description of the whole worlde.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Geography --  Early wors to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:1"/>
            <p>A GEOGRAPHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL AND AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologicall deſcription of all the Empires and Kingdomes, both of <hi>Continent and Ilands in this</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall Globe. Relating their ſcituations, manners, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Prouinces, and</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernements.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Arsiam naturam ſuperat, nam pendere Terra, </l>
               <l>Quam facit haec facit hic pictor habere pedes.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Creede, featuring a griffon seated on a stone or book, resting on a ball or globe with wings (McKerrow 339)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Simon VVaterſon,</hi> dwelling at <hi>the Signe of the Crowne in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> 1607.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>In inſequeus Geographium opus Decaſtichon.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <l>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id perigrinandi prodeſt tot adire labores.</l>
               <l>Dum quod vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> petis poſſis habere domi?</l>
               <l>Quae mare, quae tellus, quae tanta pericula monſtrant,</l>
               <l>Haec vno obtatu parvula charta docet.</l>
               <l>Non hîc Scylla vorax, aut formidanda Caribdis.</l>
               <l>Temperat has placidas mitior auſter aquas.</l>
               <l>Hic tu cum cern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ernas polyphemon in antro.</l>
               <l>Non aper hic fertat dente vel vnque Leo.</l>
               <l>Ergo quid vlterius ſatagis? Habet omnia habentem</l>
               <l>Qui mundum, mundus quod tenet, ille tenet.</l>
               <byline>Io: Prideaux.</byline>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <l>FLevit Alexander cum plures audijt orbes,</l>
               <l>Tu potius plures non Iore flere potes.</l>
               <l>Ille dolens vnum quod non ſuperaverit, omnes</l>
               <l>Armis deſperat viuere poſſe ſuis.</l>
               <l>Tam bene tu veterem cum iam deſcripſeris orbem</l>
               <l>Nunc cupias alium poſſe videre novum.</l>
               <l>Ne doleas: nam ſi non primus ſufficit orbis</l>
               <l>Quo tua ſe ſaturet Muſa, ſecundus erit.</l>
               <l>Interea <hi>Safforte</hi> tuum (quo pinxeris orbem)</l>
               <l>Stabit forte (vetus dum cadet orbis) opus.</l>
               <byline>Caſparus Tomannus.</byline>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:18337:3"/>
               <l>NOn capiunt muſcas, nec ſepe minutis,</l>
               <l>Ingentes animi rebus adeſſe ſolent.</l>
               <l>Audaces fortuna invat, timor arguit autem,</l>
               <l>Degeneres animos: hoc tua caepta ſonant,</l>
               <l>Cui genus antiqnum iuvenis, quem terra nec vndae,</l>
               <l>Nee vaſti spatium terruit oceani.</l>
               <l>Quae tu tam dextre pinxiſti cuncta: referre</l>
               <l>Et genus, &amp; proaves vt videare tuos.</l>
               <l>Ergo age, iam notus, ſi nox tibi ſufficit orbis,</l>
               <l>Ignotos adeas inipiger Antipodes.</l>
               <byline>Iohannes Glanuillae.</byline>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, admired of men, and myrrour of <hi>women, the Lady</hi> Elizabeth Ruſſel Dowager, my worthy Lady and Miſtreſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, It may ſeeme ſtrange to your learned cenſure, to finde him the Author of a booke, which ſo lately was your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Page: But the ſeedes then ſowne were ſuch, and their manuring ſithens of that qualitie, that the ground had been too barren, if no fruit had followed. Little (God knowes) it is, and that very vntimely, vnable to endure the leaſt blaſt of our moderne Critickes; were it not fauourably ſheltered by your Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Patronage; whoſe rare learning &amp; vertues, the world rather honoureth, then imitateth; my ſelfe am fitter to admire, then expreſſe. The very conceit whereof, heartened mee to circuit the whole earth, in it to finde ſomething to preſent
<pb facs="tcp:18337:4"/> your Honour. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si natura nigat facit indignatio verſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sat.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Meere chafing, made Iuuenall a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et,</hi> and me a Geographer: an ardent contention to acknowledge my dutie which ſufficiently to performe, I eſteeme my ſelfe too vnworthy, and the whole world too little. The thing herein I aime at, is your benigne acceptance, in confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whereof, I haue preſumed ſo farre; which ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this your manifold former fauours, my hopes are attained, and my ſelfe bound,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours in all ſeruice and dutie to be commaunded.</hi> Rob. Stafforde.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader (for ſo I ſuppoſe thee to be, vntil I find thee contrary) thou art little beholding to me for this Geographical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as containing little in it worth thy peruſing, and that which it is, thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my will. Hardly I thinke I ſhall ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee, who neuer in this kinde could ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelfe: yet thus farre importunity hath forced mee, and whatſoeuer thou findeſt, is more then my ſelfe intended, or thou couldeſt of me expect. A poore Suruey here thou haſt, not of my trauels but reading: If ſometime therefore errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I patronize it not, but relate it. So far thou mayeſt beleeue me, that what my ſelfe beleeue not, I inuented not, but tooke out of others. The Methode I had from my Tutor, and ſo far forth the reſt, that I account it but the gleanings of his plentifull Harueſt. The rather to be allowed (as I take it) becauſe it admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth without maime the cancelling of a fiction, and the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of any notable thing omitted. If thy profit by it coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile my paines, thou haſt ſomewhat: if otherwiſe, the brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it cannot looſe thee much time. They which haue no leiſure to ſeeke farther, may take this for an inſight: others may fetch a great deale more from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whom I had this, to whoſe riper iudgements I truſt my youth may excuſe mee, when the worke cannot. As for the Punies of mine owne ranke,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carpere vel noli noſtra vel ede tua:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Martial.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Shall ſerue for a counterblaſt. And ſo I commend this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, to the world: and thy ſelfe and it to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of both. Not determining to trouble thee any more for ought I know, and therefore reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine as thou vſest me,</hi> R. Staff.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:5"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the Author.</head>
               <l>WHen <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſitting in Imperiall Robe,</l>
               <l>was Soueraign Lord of th' earth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding Rome,</l>
               <l>He ſent to meaſure this terreſtriall Globe,</l>
               <l>To ſee how much was left to ouercome.</l>
               <l>Belike his Kingdomes Vice-Royes were too ſlacke,</l>
               <l>In due performance of this weighty taske,</l>
               <l>Or he ſome good Geographers did lacke,</l>
               <l>That might in briefe reſolue what he did aske.</l>
               <l>Whilſt he intended all the world to gaine,</l>
               <l>He in the Senate houſe was ſtabd to death.</l>
               <l>A little Vrne his aſhes did containe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe mind was not content with halfe the earth:</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou (deare friend) liu'd in this Monarkes dayes,</l>
               <l>And rendred vp this booke vnto his hands,</l>
               <l>He would haue crown'd thee with tryumphall Bayes,</l>
               <l>Or made thee ruler of ſome forreine lands:</l>
               <l>For this ſmall booke (yet great in worth) doth ſhow</l>
               <l>All that which mighty Caeſar crau'd to know.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In idem opus Carmen Encomiaſticon.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>VT Microcoſmus Homo eſt ſimulachrum Regis Olympi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic Maiore minor pulchrior orbe foret.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Factus erat Magnus Mundi ratione Minoris,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scire licet patulo quicquid in orbe latet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O Tu qui externas ignarus tendis ad Oras,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hunc diſcas librum mira legenao loqui.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic mores hominum graphicè depingit, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et quicquia magnum ſub lone Caeſar habet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hîc, campos, ſtuutos, montes, Capitolia turres,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Structa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Mygdonio marmore tecta, legas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hîc fractos Regum tumulos, ſtratoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Coloſſos,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rupta<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Montiuagae Templa Sacrata Deae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hîc, vbi Troia fuit, magnae &amp; Carthaginis arces,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> erat armipotens Roma vetuſta ſcias,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terra Arabum foelix, vbi Phaenix naſcitur vnus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plus foelix, multos terra Britanna tulit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haec multos parit ingento, Gento<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> potentes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Parua ſed eximij: Inſula culta viris.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inter quos ſemper meus eſt memoranous amicus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui dulce, &amp; nobis vtile texit opus.</hi>
               </l>
               <byline>Tho. Rogers.</byline>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:5"/>
            <head>A GEOGRAPHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL AND ANTHOLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall deſcription of the whole World.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. DE GEOGRAPHIA.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eographie</hi> is an Imitation of the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">Definition.</note> of the whole earth, with thoſe thinges which are annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. <hi>Ptolm. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. Therefore it comprehendeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>Chorographie,</hi> the deſcription of a Region, <hi>Hydrographie,</hi> the diſcription of waters, <hi>Topographie,</hi> the deſcription of a place, and the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The Subiect of <hi>Geographie,</hi> is this Terreſtriall <note place="margin">Subiect.</note> Globe, compoſed of earth and water, ſo far forth as the parts of it, haue a diuerſe ſcituation, as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the heauens, as one towards another. <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> pag. 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Concerning the Terreſtriall Globe in reſpect of the Heauens, two things are dilligently to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, <hi>Longitude</hi> and <hi>Latitude</hi> of places.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>Longitude</hi> of a place, is a diſtance inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted betweene the firſt <hi>Meridian,</hi> which paſſeth <note place="margin">Longitude.</note> through the <hi>Canarie Ilands,</hi> and the <hi>Meridian</hi> of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18337:6"/> place, which <hi>Longitude</hi> is alwayes to be meaſured from Weſt vnto Eaſt in the degrees of the <hi>Aequator.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe all <hi>Meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> cut the <hi>Aequator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 The <hi>Latitude</hi> of a place, is a diſtance intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Latitude.</note> betweene the <hi>Aequator,</hi> and any place North or South from it, which to finde out, turne the place in the Globe, vntill it come directly vnder the brazen Meridian, then numbring in the brazen Meridian, how many degrees be betwixt the <hi>Aequator</hi> and the place, it ſhewes the <hi>Latitude</hi> directly.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Longitude and Latitude beeing knowne of a place, it is eaſie to finde it in any globe; and on the contrarie, if you ſee the place firſt in the globe, by turning it vnder the brazen meridian, both the Longitude and Latitude is knowne.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Concerning the <hi>Terreſtriall Globe,</hi> in regard of his partes one vnto the other, it is diuided into Sea, and Land.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The <hi>Sea</hi> or <hi>Ocean,</hi> is a huge water compaſſing about this whole <hi>Vniuerſe,</hi> whoſe partes paſſing by <note place="margin">Sea.</note> many particular places; are called by ſundrie &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular names, as <hi>Mare Britanicum, à Britania, Mare Mediterraneum: quia mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>inter duas terras, africae &amp; Europae. Mare Atlanticum</hi> of the great mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain <hi>Atlas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 In the Sea, are to bee conſidered three things: Creekes, Straights, and Hauens.</p>
               <p n="9">9 A Creeke is a place where the Sea doth runne <note place="margin">Sinus.</note> any where into the boſome of the earth: And ſuch are <hi>Sinus Arabicus,</hi> or the redde Sea: <hi>Sinus Perſicus,</hi> or <hi>Mare Balſerum, Sinus Adriaticus,</hi> or the <hi>Gulfe of Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Fretum,</hi> is a narrowe ſtraight, or Arme of the Sea, paſsing betwixt two Lands, ſo called <hi>a Fremitu.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Fretum.</note>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18337:6"/> Whereof the chiefe are, <hi>Fretum Gaditaneum,</hi> or the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltar, Fretum Magellanicum,</hi> or the ſtraights of <hi>Magellane: Fretum Naſſouicum,</hi> or the North Straights.</p>
               <p n="11">11 A Hauen is a litle Creeke or entrance into the <note place="margin">Portes.</note> maine Ocean, where ſhippes are alwayes reſted and harbored.</p>
               <p n="12">12 The Earth, as may be ſeene in all Geographi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <note place="margin">Earth.</note> Maps and tables, is deſcribed and paynted forth with huge Mountaines, great Woods, faire Riuers, and many famous Cities: the circuit of it, is 21600. miles, and (as ſome write,) if a footman had a path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way round about the World, hee might goe it in 900. dayes. <hi>Magiuus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 In the Earth are to be conſidered &amp; obſerued, two things, the <hi>Ilands,</hi> and the <hi>Continent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 An Iland, <hi>(quaſi, eye of land,)</hi> is compaſt round <note place="margin">Iland.</note> about with the Sea, as <hi>Britania, Hybernia, Sardinia,</hi> &amp;c: Of the Latins it is called <hi>Inſula, quaſi in Salo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 A <hi>Continent</hi> is a great quantitie of land not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided <note place="margin">Continent.</note> by waters, where many Kingdomes and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires are lincked and ioyned together. As <hi>Spaine, France, Germany.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="16">16 In both Ilands and Continent, three things are to be noted: <hi>Istmus, Peninſula,</hi> &amp; <hi>Promontorium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 An <hi>Iſtmus</hi> or <hi>Cherſoneſus</hi> is a narrow or <hi>ſtraight</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Istmus.</note> land between two Seas. Of which, the moſt famous are <hi>Istmus Corinthiacus,</hi> and <hi>Istmus Cymbricus,</hi> both in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>Peninſula (quaſi pene Inſula)</hi> is a part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, euery where inuironed with the Sea, vnleſſe <note place="margin">Penin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula.</note> it be where it is tyed vnto the firme land, with a little
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18337:7"/> 
                  <hi>Iſtmus.</hi> The moſt farre fam'de of which are, whole <hi>Africa, Scandia, Taurica Cherſoneſus, Pelloponeſus</hi> or <hi>Morea,</hi> and <hi>Peruana</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19 A <hi>Promontorie,</hi> is a high Mountaine, which <note place="margin">Promo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tory</note> bendeth it ſelfe into the Sea, the extreame or end of which, is called a <hi>Cape.</hi> Of which, the moſt known are the <hi>Cape of good Hope,</hi> in <hi>Africa:</hi> the <hi>Cape of Saint Vincent,</hi> in <hi>Portugall:</hi> the <hi>Cape Comari</hi> in <hi>Aſia:</hi> and the <hi>Cape de la Victoria,</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the vnknowne parts of the Earth.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Etherto haue I ſet downe the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall affections of the Terreſtriall globe. Now therefore will I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto particulars, and onely, &amp; particularly ſpeake of the earth, becauſe <hi>Hydrographie</hi> doth rather belong vnto the art of Nauigation.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The partes of the Earth are either vnknowne, or knowne.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The vnknowne partes which lye in obſcuritie, are eyther in the <hi>North</hi> vnder the <hi>Articke Pole,</hi> or in the <hi>South,</hi> vnder the <hi>Antarticke Pole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The vnknowne Land which lyeth vnder the <hi>Artick Pole,</hi> is ſeparated euery where (as it is thought) from the other partes of the World, with the <hi>North Sea,</hi> which breaking in by 19. Inletts, &amp; 4. Staights,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18337:7"/> is ſupped vp, &amp; ingulft into the bowells of the earth, vnder the blacke Rocke, which lyeth directly vnder the Pole, being in compaſſe 33. Leucars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iames Cnoyen</hi> in the booke of his trauells, maketh mention of a certaine Prieſt of <hi>Noruegia,</hi> which had by tradition from a Frier of <hi>Oxford,</hi> that by the help of his magicke, and taking the fitteſt opportunitie of time, hee vndertooke to trauell into thoſe parts, and was directly vnder the Pole, where he deſcryed all theſe things. <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Not far diſtant from the blacke Rocke are ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated foure Ilands of reaſonable bigneſſe, the Sea running betweene euerie one of them, and making them equall in quantitie one vnto the other. In one of the which Ilands beeing oppoſite vnto <hi>Biarmia,</hi> are found Pigmies or little men, not aboue 4. foote in height. <hi>Magin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 The vnknowne Land, which lyeth vnder the <hi>Antarticke Pole,</hi> is thought to be greater then all the earth beſides.</p>
               <p n="7">7 In it are deſcried ſome fewe Prouinces, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Guynea, Terra del Fuego Pſittacorum Regio, Lucach, Reach,</hi> and <hi>Maletur.</hi> All which together, are called <hi>Magelane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe Countryes nothing can be certainely ſpoken, only that in the land <hi>del Fuego</hi> there is much ſmoke, in <hi>Pſittacorum regione,</hi> there are great Parrets, in <hi>Beach,</hi> Golde: in <hi>Maletur Spices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 The Inhabitants of theſe Regions which haue bene ſeene (beeing very fewe) goe naked, and are moſt barbarous people. <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18337:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the knowne parts of the Earth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He vnknowne parts of the World haue beene obſcurely ſpoken of. Now followeth the deſcription of the knowne parts, which are ſoure in number, <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>OF EVROPE.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>EVrope</hi> (called by <hi>Plinie</hi> the faireſt of all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,) is on the South, ſeparated (from <hi>Africa)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> with the <hi>Straights of Gibraltar,</hi> and the <hi>Mediterr anean Sea,</hi> on the Weſt (from <hi>America,)</hi> with the rowling waues of the <hi>Atlanticke Ocean,</hi> and on the Eaſt (from <hi>Aſia,)</hi> with the <hi>Egaean Sea, Helleſpont, Propontus, Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, Boſpherus, Pontus Euxinus, Boſpherus Cimirius, Maeotis Palus, Tanais fluuium,</hi> &amp; ſo drawing vp a line vnto the riuer <hi>Duina,</hi> which runneth along vnto the Port of <hi>Saint Nicholas,</hi> disburdning it ſelfe into <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Granuicus,</hi> or the <hi>North Sea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The forme of <hi>Europe</hi> is like vnto a Dragon, the <note place="margin">Simititude</note> head being <hi>Spaine,</hi> &amp; the wings <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 In Longitude it is 3800. miles, reaching from <note place="margin">Longitude</note> the Cape of <hi>Saint Vincent</hi> in <hi>Portugal,</hi> vnto <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> in <hi>Thracia. Magin. Orteli.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 In Latitude, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth 1200. miles, ſtretching <note place="margin">Latitude.</note> it ſelfe from the <hi>Archipelago</hi> or <hi>Egaean Sea,</hi> vnto <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Congelatum,</hi> or the <hi>Frozen Ocean.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18337:8"/>
                  <p n="5"> 5 The people or inhabitants of it, doth farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note> the reſidue of the other parts, in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Artes, valor and ciuilitie. And are all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, vnles it be towards the northeren part of <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> or thoſe which are vnder the Tyrannicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Turke. <hi>Magin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. In <hi>Europe</hi> are to be conſidered two thinges: Firſt, the Kingdomes and Empires which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within the Continent, and then the Ilands.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Firſt therefore of the Continent, in which are <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> contained 16. Kingdomes, <hi>Spaine, France, Germanie, Belgia, Dania, Italie, Illyria, Hungarie, Polonia, Pruſſia,</hi> the <hi>Turkiſh Empire in Europe, Tranſiluania, Lituania, Liuonia, Scandia, Moſcouia,</hi> or <hi>Ruſſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF SPAINE.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>SPaine</hi> is in euery place enuironed with the Sea, <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> vnles it be towards the north-eaſt part, where it is ioyned vnto <hi>France,</hi> diſtinguiſhed only by the high <hi>Pyrinean mountains.</hi> It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines in circuit, 1890. miles.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 This land is very fertill, enricht with all kindes <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> of wine, Sugar, all ſortes of fruites, graines, oyles, mettalls, eſpecially of Golde and Siluer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of it are verie <hi>ceremonious, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note> 
                        <hi>proude, hypocrites, laborious,</hi> addicted more then any other Nation vnto <hi>Melancholy,</hi> and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the <hi>Gothes, Saracens,</hi> and <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 This kingdome is diuided into many Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereof the chiefe are firſt, <hi>Portugal,</hi> famous for <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Nauigation,</hi> in which the chiefe citie is <hi>Lisbone:</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Granado,</hi> or <hi>Andalucia,</hi> in which are the beſt horſes: the chiefe citie in it is <hi>Siuill,</hi> from whence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18337:9"/> come our excellent ciuill Oranges: in this Prouince is alſo <hi>Cadiz</hi> or <hi>Cales,</hi> that was once ſurpriſed by <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen:</hi> the third Prouince is <hi>Caſteile,</hi> in which is that great citie <hi>Tolledo,</hi> the Byſhoprick wherof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neere in reuenues vnto the Popedome: the fourth is <hi>Nauarre,</hi> in which ſtands the city <hi>Bilbao,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we haue ſo many excellent tride blades: the fift &amp; laſt is <hi>Galicia,</hi> in which ſtandeth <hi>S. Iago:</hi> where <hi>Saint Iames</hi> is much reuerenced. <hi>Ortel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 The chiefe riuers of theſe prouinces are foure, <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> 
                        <hi>Tagus,</hi> in which is found much golden Sande: <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diana</hi> or <hi>Ana,</hi> which runneth into a Cauerne or hole of the earth, for a great ſpace, and riſeth vp againe. <hi>Guadalquiuir,</hi> vppon whoſe bancks ſtand <hi>Siuill.</hi> And the laſt is <hi>Duerus. Merula.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 In times paſt this was diuided into 12. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <note place="margin">Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but nowe it is onely one entire Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſubiected vnto one King: who is called, <hi>King of Spaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF FRANCE.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>FRance</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with <hi>Mare Aquitani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> &amp; the <hi>Pyrinea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mountains:</hi> on the North, with the <hi>Engliſh Sea:</hi> on the South, with <hi>Mare Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum:</hi> on the Eaſt, with <hi>Germanie:</hi> &amp; on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt, with the <hi>Alpes. Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 This country is extraordinary fruitfull, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> almoſt in euery thing, eſpecially in <hi>Corne, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Salt,</hi> which cauſeth that ſaying, that <hi>France</hi> hath three Loadſtones to draw riches from forraine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Corne</hi> caried into <hi>Spaine, Wines</hi> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported into <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Salte,</hi> wherewith the whole kingdom &amp; bordering Nations are ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully ſtored.</p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18337:9"/>
                     <p n="3"> 3 The Inhabitants of this Land are in the firſt onſet <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> of any thing very vehement, but at the length as ſlowe and dull. In their words only verball, in their deeds cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous: from whence it is ſaid; that <hi>the Frenchman ſings not as hee prickes, pronounceth not as he writes, ſpeakes not as hee thinkes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 The Prouinces of this Region are manie, among which, three of them haue free Princes. The firſt is <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> in which the chiefe cittie is <hi>Nancie:</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Burgundie,</hi> whoſe <hi>Metrapollitane</hi> and chiefe cittie is <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſançon,</hi> lying vpon the riuer <hi>Doux;</hi> the third is <hi>Subaudia,</hi> or <hi>Sauoye,</hi> whoſe chiefeſt citie is <hi>Geneua,</hi> ſcituated vpon a faire &amp; pleaſant Lake, and in which they haue a law, that if any offender flie for refuge thither, the law doth as wel take holde on him there, as in the place where hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the crime.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 The other prouinces are many, among which the chief are eight. Firſt, the Prouince of <hi>Normandie,</hi> whoſe <hi>Metrapolitane</hi> citie is <hi>Roan,</hi> famous for trafficke, in manie forraine countries: the ſecond is <hi>Britanie,</hi> whoſe chiefe citie is <hi>Breſt:</hi> the third is <hi>Burges</hi> or <hi>Berrie,</hi> whoſe chiefe citie is called <hi>Burges,</hi> which (as <hi>Iohn Calmenus</hi> affirmes) hath an Vniuerſitie in it, worthy to be intituled: <hi>The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all learning, &amp; ſtore houſe of learned men.</hi> The fourth is <hi>Aquitanie,</hi> in which ſtands <hi>Tolouſe,</hi> that beautifull, beſt peopled, and moſt ancienteſt citie of <hi>France,</hi> next vnto <hi>Paris:</hi> the fift is <hi>Picardie,</hi> in which the chiefe citie is <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens:</hi> the ſixt is <hi>Poictou,</hi> in which is the citie <hi>Poictiers:</hi> the ſeuenth is <hi>Languedocke:</hi> and the eight is <hi>Aniou:</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others there are, which to rehearſe, would be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and therefore I omit them.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The Riuers of note in theſe Prouinces, are foure. <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> The firſt is <hi>Sequana</hi> or <hi>Seine,</hi> which runneth through the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18337:10"/> faireſt and Metrapolitane Citie of <hi>France,</hi> called <hi>Paris,</hi> or <hi>Lutetia, (quaſi in luto ſita.)</hi> The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is <hi>Loyre,</hi> vpon whoſe ſhores ſtand <hi>Angiers</hi> &amp; <hi>Orleance,</hi> two famous cities. The 3. is <hi>Rhodanus</hi> or <hi>Rhoſne:</hi> the 4. &amp; laſt of any note is <hi>Garo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 Two things are reported of this Countrey, very ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. The one is, that the King cureth a certain wenne, <note place="margin">Wonders.</note> which riſeth in a mans neck, with the touch of his hand, ſaying theſe words: <hi>Sanet te Deus, tangit te Rex.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, that ther is a certain oyle in the church of <hi>Rheims,</hi> which as they report, was ſent from Heauen: and the Kings being annointed with it euery Coronation day, it doth neuer decreaſe. <hi>Hondius in Tabulis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8 This Kindome is gouerned by a Monarchicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, ſubiected vnto one ſole <hi>King,</hi> who is called <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> the king of <hi>France,</hi> and his eldeſt ſonne is tituled the <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> From this countrie is excluded by the <hi>Salick lawe,</hi> any woman, that ſhee cannot raigne and be Queene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF GERMANIE.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>GErmany,</hi> is diſtinguiſhed on the weſt from <hi>France,</hi> by <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> part of the riuer <hi>Rheine,</hi> and a line, which is drawen vp directly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Strasburg</hi> vnto <hi>Cales:</hi> on the South, from <hi>Italie,</hi> with the <hi>Alpes:</hi> on the South-eaſt, with <hi>Iſtria,</hi> and <hi>Illyrica:</hi> and on the Eaſt with <hi>Hungarie, Polonia,</hi> and the riuer <hi>Viſtula. Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 This countrie is inricht with all ſortes of <hi>Mines,</hi> as <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> well of <hi>Salt,</hi> as of <hi>Mettalls.</hi> It hath alſo great abundance of <hi>corne, wine, ſaffron, fruits, hote bathes, &amp; ſweete fountaines.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The Inhabitants of this Empire are generallie very tall, goodly, warlike, and faithfull men, little addicted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> venerie, but much affecting drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, that welſpring of Impietie, from whence bubbleth out this ſaying of them, that <hi>Germanus potat quantum poteſt: &amp; Germanorum</hi>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18337:10"/> 
                        <hi>viuere, eſt bibere.</hi> They are alſo for their inuentions in <note place="margin">Inuentions.</note> arts Mechanicall moſt excellent, and farre ſurpaſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other Nation: for from them came the inuention of Gunnes, inuented of one <hi>Bertholdus Swart,</hi> in the yeare 1378. by them was alſo inuented Printing, in the yeare of our Lord, 1440. by one <hi>Ihon Gutemberg,</hi> but (as <hi>Ramus</hi> affirmes,) by one <hi>Iohn Fuſt,</hi> who printed <hi>Tullies Offices,</hi> which was the firſt booke that euer was printed.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 In the middle of <hi>Germany</hi> is ſcituated <hi>Bohemia,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Bohemia.</note> pleaſant kingdom, compaſt about with a wood called <hi>Sylua Hyrcinia:</hi> the chiefe citie of it is <hi>Prage,</hi> in which the Emperour doth keepe his Court.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 There are alſo in this great &amp; large Dominion ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> Prouinces, among which, the eſpeciall, firſt <hi>Saxonie,</hi> whoſe Metrapolitane citie is <hi>Witteberg,</hi> lying vppon the Riuer <hi>Albis:</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Brande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bourg:</hi> in which ſtands <hi>Franckford,</hi> ſcituated vppon the Riuer <hi>Odera:</hi> in which there is an Vniuerſitie, erected by <hi>Marques Ioachim,</hi> in the yeare, 1506. The third is <hi>Pomerania,</hi> the chiefe Citie of which is <hi>Stetim.</hi> The fourth is <hi>Bauaria,</hi> whoſe beſt cittie is <hi>Munchen.</hi> The fift is <hi>Sleſia,</hi> in which is ſcituated the city <hi>Breſſel.</hi> The ſixt is <hi>Franconia,</hi> whoſe moſt noted Citie is <hi>Franckford,</hi> founded vppon the riuer <hi>Moenum,</hi> in which <note place="margin">Martes.</note> place is alwayes the Election of the Emperour, and the famous Martes for bookes. The ſeuenth is <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Metrapolitan of which, is that famous <hi>Vienna,</hi> ſeated vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the riuer <hi>Danubius,</hi> eſteemed to be one one of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Citties in <hi>Germanie.</hi> The eight and laſt, worthy to <note place="margin">Heluetia.</note> be preferred before all the reſt, is <hi>Switzerland</hi> or <hi>Heluetia,</hi> which is diuided into 13. Cantones or chiefe cities with their Apendices, the gouernment of them beeing onely popular: for although the members ſeeme to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet liue they as one bodie, firmly knit &amp; vnited, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18337:11"/> one hauing his particular Magiſtrate and Councell.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The moſt famous Riuers of theſe Prouinces are ſixe. Firſt is the great <hi>Danubius,</hi> which doth receiue into <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> it 60. Nauigable Riuers, before it is disburdened into <hi>Pontus Euxinus:</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Rhene,</hi> from whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the beſt Rheniſh wine, &amp; vpon whoſe banke is ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated the citie <hi>Strasburge</hi> or <hi>Argentine,</hi> in which ther is a towre of 578. <hi>Geometricall paces high,</hi> counted the eight Miracle of the world: the third is <hi>Amaſus:</hi> the fourth is <hi>Moenus:</hi> the fift is <hi>Odera:</hi> and the ſixt is <hi>Albis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 The Emperours do not ſucceed, but are alwaies cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by theſe 6. Electors: the <hi>Arch-byſhops of Ments, Triers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Colen:</hi> the <hi>Countie Palatine of Rhene:</hi> the <hi>Duke of Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Marqueſſe of Brandeburge.</hi> If theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not agree, then doth the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> decide the controuerſie.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 Concerning the Gouernment of this Empire, it hath manie free Princes, which is the reaſon that the Emperour by ſome is called a King of Kings. <note place="margin">Gouernment</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF BELGIA.</head>
                     <p>1 <hi>BElgia,</hi> (or the Lowe Countreyes,) is limited on the <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> Eaſt, with Germanie: on the South, with France: on the Weſt, with the mayne Ocean: &amp; on the North, with Denmarke and part of the great Sea. It contayneth in circuit 1000. Italian miles.</p>
                     <p>2 This Countrie doeth moſt excell in all manner of Linnen, and fine Stuffes: and about <hi>Friſea, Gelderland,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> and <hi>Holland,</hi> they haue Oxen of ſuch an incredible big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which if they were ballanced, would weigh aboue 2000. poundes, for there was ſeene in Antwerpe, a Bull, whoſe bodie did exceede 3200. weight. <hi>Magin. Ortel.</hi> In this Countrie there is alſo great abundance of <hi>Butter, Cheeſe, Herring,</hi> and <hi>Salmon,</hi> and eſpecially in Holland.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18337:11"/>
                     <p> 3 The Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are very goodly &amp; propermen, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> generally well proportionated legs. They are great drinkers, not proud nor enuious, but vnmindfull both of benefits done vnto them, &amp; of iniuries offered. They are excellent Muſitians, &amp; in Mechanicall arts moſt expert. <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>4 The prouinces of <hi>Belgia</hi> are 17. in which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained 4. <hi>Dukedomes,</hi> 7. <hi>Earldomes,</hi> 5. <hi>Barondries,</hi> &amp; 1. <hi>Marqueſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>5 The 4. Dukedomes are firſt, <hi>Brabant,</hi> in which the <note place="margin">1. <hi>Brabant.</hi>
                        </note> chiefe citie is <hi>Antwerp,</hi> fortified with 10. royall Bulwarks, and hauing within it a Towne-houſe, whoſe circuite is 4812. paces. There is alſo in this Prouince an Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie called <hi>Louaine. Ortel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6 The ſecond Dukedom is <hi>Liege</hi> or <hi>Luicke,</hi> called by <note place="margin">2. <hi>Liege.</hi>
                        </note> ſome the Paradiſe of Prieſts: the chiefe city is <hi>Liege,</hi> from whence the Dukedome taketh his name.</p>
                     <p>7 The third is <hi>Lutzenburge,</hi> in which is the great Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt <note place="margin">3. <hi>Lutzen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge.</hi>
                        </note> of <hi>Ardenna,</hi> which was in the time of <hi>Caeſar</hi> 500. miles in le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, at this day only 90. the chief city is <hi>Lutze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>burg. or.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>8 The 4. and laſt Dukedome is <hi>Gelderland,</hi> noted <note place="margin">4. <hi>Gelderla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</hi>
                        </note> chiefly for the excellent paſture groundes, which are in it, the chiefe citie is <hi>Nimmegen. Ortel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>9 The 7. Earledoms or Counties, are firſt <hi>Flanders,</hi> in <note place="margin">1. <hi>Flandres.</hi>
                        </note> which the chiefe city is <hi>Gaunt,</hi> there are alſo many ſtrong Port towns in it, as <hi>Newport, Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kerk, Oſtend,</hi> &amp; <hi>Slewis. Ort.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>10 The ſecond is <hi>Artois,</hi> the chiefe citie of which is <note place="margin">2. <hi>Artois.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Arras,</hi> from whence commeth the beſt cloth of <hi>Arras.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>11 The third is <hi>Hainolt,</hi> whoſe faireſt city is <hi>Mons,</hi> in which there is a Capitall of Religious women, that was <note place="margin">3. <hi>Hainolt.</hi>
                        </note> erected by <hi>Vadruda,</hi> Dutches of <hi>Lorraine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>12 The 4. is <hi>Holland,</hi> very poore of it ſelf, vnles it be in paſture grounds, in which they nouriſh ſo many Cattell <note place="margin">4. <hi>Holland.</hi>
                        </note> that it doth excell other parts in Butter and cheeſe. They are alſo ſo ſtrong at Sea, that they are able to make 800.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18337:12"/> great ſhips, and twice ſo many ſmall. The chiefe citie is <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> ſo famous for Trafficke, that there may be ſeen in her Port ſomtimes, 500. great ſhips at once. <hi>Ortel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>13 The fift is <hi>Zealand (quaſi Sea and Land,)</hi> in which <note place="margin">5. <hi>Zealand.</hi>
                        </note> countrie or Countie there is found no freſh water. In it is alſo very little wood. The chiefe citie is <hi>Middelborough,</hi> in the Iland of <hi>Walcheren.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>14 The ſixt is <hi>Zutphen,</hi> of which very little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <note place="margin">6. <hi>Zutphen.</hi>
                        </note> can be ſpoken.</p>
                     <p>15 The 7. and laſt Countie is <hi>Namur,</hi> verie plentifull <note place="margin">7. <hi>Namur.</hi>
                        </note> of Woods and Deare, the chiefe citie is <hi>Namur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>16 The 5. <hi>Barondries</hi> or Lordſhips are firſt, <hi>Friezland,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltrect.</note> the noted cities whereof are <hi>Leuorden</hi> and <hi>Embden.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>17 The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is <hi>Vltrect,</hi> whoſe chiefeſt city is <hi>Vtreck.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>17 The third is <hi>Mechlin:</hi> the fourth is <hi>Oueriſſel:</hi> the fift and laſt Lordſhip is <hi>Groining.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>18 The 17. Prouince is, the <hi>Marquiſet</hi> of the holie Empire, in which nothing is famous.</p>
                     <p>19 The moſt noted Riuers of theſe Prouinces are three, the firſt of which is <hi>Rhene,</hi> mentioned before in <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> 
                        <hi>Germanie:</hi> the next it <hi>Schald,</hi> which waſheth the bancks of <hi>Antwerpe:</hi> the laſt is <hi>Meuſe,</hi> vpon whoſe ſhore is ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated <hi>Luicke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>20 This Country (famous for wars) is in part gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> by manie, whom they call <hi>States of the lowe Countries.</hi> But the <hi>Arche-duke of Auſtria</hi> wageth warre continuallie with them, to bring it vnder his Dominion, claiming and laying Title vnto it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF DENMARKE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DEnmarke</hi> is enuironed round with the maine Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <note place="margin">Limites.</note> vnleſſe it be on the South, where it is ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18337:12"/>
                     <p> 2 This Kingdome doth abound in goodly Horſes, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> and in ſuch ſtore of cattell, that there are yearely carried into <hi>Germanie</hi> 50000. Oxen. There is alſo ſuch infinite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of herring, (neare vnto the Ile <hi>Scania)</hi> that the ſhips are ſcarce able by maine ſtrength of Owers to rowe out of the Harbour, the fiſh lying ſo thicke, that their quantitie is ſuppoſed to ſurpaſſe the water it ſelfe. <hi>Ortel.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>3 The Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this country are very valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both at land and Sea, in their Religion they are all <hi>Lutherans.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4 The Prouinces of this Kingdome are almoſt all <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Ilands,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which, the chiefe are firſt, <hi>Sealand,</hi> in which is <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> the chiefe ſeate of the King, and an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, in it is alſo <hi>Roſchilt,</hi> where the Kings are ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toombed. The ſecond is <hi>Loilant,</hi> in which there growe ſo many Hazell-nuts, that ſhippes are loaded there with them. The third is <hi>Fimera,</hi> in which <hi>Ticho Brahe</hi> built a Caſtle by Arte, to the wonder of euery body that hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene it. In the Continent are containd two other Prouinces, <hi>Iugtland,</hi> and <hi>Holſten,</hi> in which is <hi>Meldrope,</hi> the inhabitants of which are ſo riche, that they couer their houſes with copper. <hi>Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>5 In this Countrie is alſo a ſtraight Sea, paſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſome of the Ilands, called the <hi>Sound:</hi> which by <note place="margin">Sound.</note> reaſon of the Impoſts and Cuſtoms of the Ships which paſſe that way, yeeldeth great gaine and profite vnto the King.</p>
                     <p>6 The Gouernment of this Kingdome is vnder one <note place="margin">Gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> ſole Prince, who is called the King of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF ITALIE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITalie,</hi> (called by <hi>Merula</hi> a Terreſtriall Paradice: The <note place="margin">Boundes.</note> Phoenix of this Maſsie round, the earths riche Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Garden of the Muſes,) is garded on the Eaſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18337:13"/> with the <hi>Adriaticke</hi> Seas on the South, with <hi>Mare Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneum:</hi> on the Weſt, with the <hi>Terrhene</hi> or <hi>Ocean:</hi> and on the North, with the <hi>Alpes,</hi> which ſeparateth it from <hi>Germanie,</hi> it is like vnto a mans legge, reaching in length from <hi>Auguſta Pretoria,</hi> vnto <hi>Otranto,</hi> which is 1010. miles, and is in breadth, in the brodeſt place, 420. miles.</p>
                     <p>2 To ſet downe the fruitfulnes of this riche Region, it may be as well declared in a line as in a leafe, for there <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> is of all things ſuch plentie, as there is not of any thing any ſcarcitie.</p>
                     <p>3 The people of this Nation are verie graue, frugall, wittie, excelling both in vertue and vices, which are in <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> luſt, monſtrous: in hate, implacable: &amp; in their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation moſt deceitfull: which had rather beſtowe any thing vpon others, then vpon themſelues: do more ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner blaſpheme then ſweare. And will rather kill a man, then giue him a diſgracefull tearme or word.</p>
                     <p>4 This Kingdome is diuided into many Prouinces, whereof the chiefe and moſt famous are fiue. <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>5 The firſt is the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> which is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then any of the reſt, full of Nobilitie, and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Naples.</note> with all things neceſſary for mans vſe. The chiefe citie of it is <hi>Naples,</hi> lying vpon the <hi>Terrhenean</hi> Sea.</p>
                     <p>6 The ſecond is the <hi>Romane Territorie,</hi> a Prouince richly furniſhed with all prouiſions, in which is ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Roma.</note> the Cittie of <hi>Rome,</hi> once called the Empreſſe of the world, as well for the beautie and Magnificence of the Citie, as for the Learning and fortitude of the Citizens: but now it is much ruinated: true Religion and vertue cleane decayed. The Gouernour of it beeing the Pope, that proud prelate, perſecutor of all true pietie, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſours.</p>
                     <p>7 The third Prouince is <hi>Lumbardie,</hi> comprehending <note place="margin">Lumbardie.</note>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18337:13"/> vnder it is the Dukedom of <hi>Millaine,</hi> which doth excell for beautie all the reſt, hauing in it many faire Riuers &amp; pleaſant Lakes: the chiefe Citie of which, is <hi>Millaine:</hi> whoſe buildings are to be admired for their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſumptuouſnes. In this Prouince is alſo the great Lake <hi>de Como,</hi> which is 60. miles in le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, &amp; vpon whoſe bankes ſtands the citie <hi>Como,</hi> in faſhion like vnto a Crab, whoſe two feete couet the water. In this Citie the two <hi>Plinies</hi> had their beginning, whoſe Fame by reaſon of their great learning, ſhall neuer haue ending. <hi>Ortelius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>8 The fourth Prouince is <hi>Tuſcanie,</hi> little inferior vnto <note place="margin">Tuſcanie.</note> the reſt in any thing, the chiefe Citie of which is <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> whoſe inhabitants (ſince the time of <hi>Macheuill,</hi> which was their <hi>Recorder,)</hi> are moſt politicke and ſubtill, amounting vnto the number of 80. thouſand perſons.</p>
                     <p>9 The fift and laſt, is the <hi>Signorie of Venice,</hi> a free <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice.</note> State, and the moſt famous of any in Chriſtendome, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by a Prince of great Maieſtie: yet both hee and his authorite ſubiected vnto the Lawes.</p>
                     <p>This Citie with the <hi>Apendices</hi> vnto it, is the richeſt &amp; beſt prouided with munition, of any Citie in <hi>Italie,</hi> as is confeſt in this particular ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſure of each Prouince, before ſpoken: that <hi>Naples</hi> excells for Nobilite: <hi>Rome</hi> for Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: <hi>Millaine</hi> for beautie, <hi>Florence</hi> for policie: but <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> for riches.</p>
                     <p>10 There is is another prouince (ſomewhat famous) called <hi>Verona,</hi> in which is the mountaine <hi>Baldo,</hi> where all profeſſors of Phiſicke doe reſort, to gather diuerſe ſortes of pretious Hearbes. And in which there is a citie called <hi>Negarino,</hi> wherin is a ſtone in forme like vnto a womans dugge, which doth continually diſtill a water, whoſe vertuous operation cauſeth a womans Milke to returne into her breſts when ſhe hath loſt it.</p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18337:14"/>
                     <p> 11 The chiefeſt riuers of theſe prouinces, are firſt <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> neer vnto which ſtands <hi>Patauine</hi> that noble Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie: <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> the next is <hi>Atheſis,</hi> adioyning vnto which is <hi>Trent,</hi> where a Councell was helde vnder <hi>Paul</hi> the third, in the yeare 1546. the next is <hi>Tiber,</hi> that runneth through the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> which when it doth ouerflowe the banks, doth betoken ſome ill fortune which ſhall befall the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: the laſt is the riuer <hi>Poe,</hi> neere vnto which ſtands <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona,</hi> a Citie of great note.</p>
                     <p>12 In this <hi>Italie,</hi> which was in time paſt, one intier Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> are nowe many abſolute States, and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by the great Pollicie of the Pope, who thought it the beſt way to make himſelfe great, by weakening the Empire.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF ILLIRIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ILliria</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with the <hi>Adriaticke</hi> Sea: on the North, with the riuer <hi>Sauus:</hi> &amp; on the Eaſt, with <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the riuer <hi>Drinus.</hi> No certaine limits can be giuen of this countrie: For all Geographers that write, doe diſagree about it.</p>
                     <p>2 The people of this land as <hi>(Liuie</hi> affirmes,) are verie <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> proude and outragious.</p>
                     <p>3 The chiefe Prouinces are three, whereof the firſt is <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Zara</hi> or <hi>Sebenine,</hi> whoſe chiefeſt citie is <hi>Zara,</hi> where (as <hi>Cornelius Sheppers</hi> doth report) is a Church called <hi>S. Iohn de Maluatia,</hi> which was built by a companie of Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that were in a dangerous tempeſt, and made a vowe that if they eſcaped, they would build a church vnto the honour of <hi>S. Ihon de Maluatia,</hi> whoſe morter ſhould be tempered with <hi>Malmeſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4 The next prouince is <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> in which the chiefe citie is <hi>Raguſus</hi> or <hi>Epidaura,</hi> where <hi>S. Ieroſme</hi> was borne.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18337:14"/>
                     <p> 5 The third and laſt is <hi>Hiſtria,</hi> which is vnder the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians.</hi> Many other Prouines there are, whereof ſome <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> are ſubiect vnto the <hi>Turke,</hi> others vnder the Dominion of <hi>Hungarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF HVNGARIE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HVngarie</hi> is bounded on the South, with the riuer <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limites.</note> on the Eaſt with the riuer <hi>Tibiſcus:</hi> on the north, with <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Ruſsia:</hi> and on the weſt, with <hi>Austria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 This country doth exceede any other for plenty of <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> corne, which thrice in a yeare is there reapt, the ground being ſo fertill that it doth almoſt growe without tilling. There are alſo ſuch infinit ſtore of Oxen, that there doth yearely paſſe through <hi>Vienna</hi> into other cuntries, 80000. beſides there are ſuch a great number of Deere, Pheſant, and Partridge, that it is lawfull for any man to hauke and hunt at his pleaſure. There is great plentie of gold, and wines, which will ſuddenly make a man drunke by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Sulpherie waters, neere vnto which the grape is gathered.</p>
                     <p>3 The people &amp; inhabitants of this Nation, are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> very ſtrong, warlike, vnkinde, and of rude behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, giuen little vnto the knowledge of Mechanick arts. They haue an order in their Countrie, that no man may weare a Feather; vnleſſe he hath killed a <hi>Turke:</hi> and they neuer reuenge particular iniuries one againſt the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, then with words, vnles the diſgracefull tear me of cowardiſe be obiected vnto them: whereof the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged is neuer freed, vntill he hath proued himſelfe in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle combate with a <hi>Turke.</hi> The Sonnes inherit equally after their Fathers death. In marrying their daughters, they giue them onely a new garment, and nothing elſe.</p>
                     <p>4 The chiefe citie of this kingdome is <hi>Buda,</hi> poſſeſſed <note place="margin">Citie.</note>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18337:15"/> now by the <hi>Turke,</hi> neere vnto which, is the fielde <hi>Zebuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis,</hi> wherein is a riuer that conuerts wood into a ſtone, &amp; the water it ſelfe being taken out turneth into a ſtone.</p>
                     <p>5 The Prouinces which are moſt mentioned in this realme are onely two: the one is the countie of <hi>Zolienſe,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> wherein there is a certaine gaping of the earth, the ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vapors of which, doth kill all the birdes that flie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it. The other is the Iland <hi>Komora</hi> (in <hi>Danubius,)</hi> the land of which is ſo fertill, that the graſſe of it doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in length the height of a man. <hi>Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7 The chiefe Riuers are <hi>Danubius, Tibiſcus, Drauus,</hi> and <hi>Sauus,</hi> all which haue great plentie of fiſh, eſpecially <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> of <hi>Salmon</hi> and <hi>Sturgeon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7 This <hi>Kingdome of Hungarie</hi> was once gouerned by <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> Spirituall men, but now it is vnder the Emperor of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> and the <hi>Turke,</hi> who haue it betwixt them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF POLONIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>POlonia</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with <hi>Germanie:</hi> on the <note place="margin">Limits.</note> Eaſt, with the riuer <hi>Boriſtines,</hi> or <hi>Neiper:</hi> on the north, with <hi>Mare Balticum,</hi> and parte of <hi>Moſcouia:</hi> and on the South, with <hi>Hungarie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 This kingdome chiefly abound in Hunnie, Waxe, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> Fiſh, Mines of Copper, Iron, Brimſtone, and in ſuch great ſtore of Horſe, that it is thought the <hi>Polanders</hi> are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vppon any neceſſitie, to raiſe 100. thouſand. In this countrie there is no wine: but in ſteede thereof, they haue an excellent kinde of <hi>Methegline.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The Inhabitants are generally braue ſouldiers, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well furniſhed with weapons, and moſt impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> if iniuries be offered them: they are very proude, thinking exceeding well of their owne worth, making
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18337:15"/> great account of anie one that will flatter them, louing braue attire and delicious meates.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 In this Kingdome are tollerated all ſorts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <note place="margin">Religion.</note> and Colledges of all ſectes, and factions: which cauſeth this ſaying, that if any one hath loſt his religion, let him goe into <hi>Poland,</hi> and hee ſhall finde it.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 The Kings ſeate and Metrapolitane Citie is <hi>Craco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Citie.</note> in which is an Vniuerſitie, ſeated vpon the banke of the riuer <hi>Viſtula.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 The moſt noted Prouinces, are firſt <hi>Podolia:</hi> the land of which is ſo fertill, that of one Sowing, they haue <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> three Harueſts, and in their meadowes the graſſe doeth growe ſo much in three dayes, that if an Oxe goe in it, his hornes cannot be ſeene.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 The next is <hi>Sammagitia,</hi> in which the people liue in cottages with their cattell and labouring Beaſts, ſome of them ſacrificing vnto a certaine Diuell, called by them <hi>Siemiennicke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8 The next is <hi>Nigra Ruſſia,</hi> in which there is great plentie of Waxe and Hunnie.</p>
                     <p n="9">9 The laſt is <hi>Maſſouia,</hi> in which the chiefe citie is <hi>Maſſouia,</hi> wherein is made the beſt <hi>Methegline.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10 The chiefe and onely Riuer of this Countrey, is <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> 
                        <hi>Viſtula.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11 This kingdome of <hi>Poland</hi> is gouerned by one ſole <note place="margin">Gouernment.</note> King, who doth not ſucceed, but is alwayes elected by, the Nobilitie of the Land.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF PRVSSIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>PRuſsia</hi> is compaſſed on the Weſt, with the riuer <hi>Viſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la:</hi> on the Eaſt, with <hi>Lituania:</hi> on the South, with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limits.</note> and on the North, with <hi>Mare Balticum,</hi> &amp; <hi>Liuonia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18337:16"/>
                     <p n="2"> 2 This countrie is moſt famous for Amber, which is found on their Sea ſhore, ſcarce any where elſe to be <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> ſeene. It is alſo well ſtored with a kinde of leather, which wee call Spruce leather.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The Inhabitants of this place are much of the ſame Nature as the <hi>Polonians</hi> are. <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 The chiefe Citie is <hi>Dantzike,</hi> ſeated vpon the riuer <hi>Viſtula.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Citie.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 The Gouernment of this countie is vnder a Duke, who doth ſubiect his power and himſelfe vnto the King <note place="margin">Gouernment.</note> of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>Of the Turks kingdome in Europe.</head>
                     <p>VNder the <hi>Turcian</hi> Empire in <hi>Europe,</hi> is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all that lyeth between the borders of <hi>Epidaurus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limites.</note> and <hi>Tanais,</hi> betweene <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea &amp; the bankes of <hi>Sauus:</hi> in which territory are comprehended many puiſſant kingdomes.</p>
                     <p>2 The <hi>Turkes</hi> are great Souldiers, patient in labour, ſparing in their foode, ſlaues vnto their Lord, great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> of their lawes, and for the reſt very inconſtant. In the Lent they abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meat in the day times, but take it out freely in the night. They acknowledge Chriſt not as the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> but as a <hi>great Prophet.</hi> They deteſt Images, &amp; wil not be called <hi>Turks;</hi> but <hi>Muſulmani,</hi> which is as much as beleeuers of the truth. Their priuate hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are moſt baſe &amp; vile, whereas their publike places are ſtately. They vſe no tables, but eate their meate on the ground, ſitting after the faſhion of Tailors vpon a ſtall, &amp; when they piſſe, they doe it with bended knees. <hi>Magi.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3 There are comprehended vnder this vaſte gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch an infinit companie of people, and ſo well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered &amp; broght vp, that one noteth theſe three things of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18337:16"/> them, which breed a terror vnto the whole world. The firſt, is their multitudes of men vnconquerable: the next, their Millitarie diſcipline vncorrupted: the laſt, Corne and prouiſion for ſtore infinite.</p>
                     <p>4 The Prouinces or rather Kingdomes of this great <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> Empire, are diuided into two parts: Into <hi>Dacia vetus,</hi> vnder which is comprehended <hi>Boſnia, Seruia, Bulgaria, Valachia, and Moldauia:</hi> and into <hi>Grecia,</hi> contained in which, are <hi>Epirus, Macedonia, Thracia, Achaia,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loponeſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>5 In <hi>Dacia vetus</hi> little is extraordinarie notable, and <note place="margin">Dacia.</note> therefore I omit the deſcription.</p>
                     <p>6 <hi>Grecia</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with the <hi>Adriaticke</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Grecia.</note> Sea: on the South, with the <hi>Mediterranean:</hi> on the Eaſt, with the <hi>Archipelago</hi> and <hi>Thracian</hi> Sea.</p>
                     <p>7 The Inhabitants of it are now very baſe, altogether <note place="margin">Inhabitanit.</note> ignorant of artes, liuing and going in their apparell after the Turkiſh manner.</p>
                     <p>8 The Prouinces as are before ſet down, are firſt <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Epirus.</note> in which <hi>Scanderbege</hi> liued, made famous by his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy acts, hee being called <hi>the ſcourge of the Turkes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>9 The next is <hi>Macedonia,</hi> for euer famoſed, by the <note place="margin">Macedonia.</note> means of him neuer to be forgotten, <hi>Alexander the great,</hi> who raigned there, being conquerour of the world: In this Prouince is <hi>Stagira,</hi> the countrie of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> and <hi>Olympus,</hi> that high topt Mountaine, aſpiring aboue the middle region of the aire.</p>
                     <p>10 The next is <hi>Romania</hi> or <hi>Thracia,</hi> a verie barren <note place="margin">Thracia.</note> place, in which ſtands the great Cittie of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein the <hi>Turke</hi> doth alwayes keepe his Court, this Citie is very populous, containing in it (as ſome write) 700000. ſoules.</p>
                     <p>11 The fourth prouince is <hi>Achaia,</hi> famous for the <note place="margin">Achaia.</note>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18337:17"/> moſt learned Vniuerſitie, which was in it, called <hi>Athens,</hi> once the nurſe of all the wittie and beſt <hi>Poets,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> and bringer vp of all eloquent and heart-winning <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricians:</hi> and in generall, it was the very heart and ſoule of humane Artes and learning. In this Prouince is alſo <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus,</hi> and <hi>Hellicon,</hi> conſecrated to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> by all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Poets.</p>
                     <p>12 The fiſt and laſt is <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> or <hi>Morea,</hi> in whoſe <note place="margin">Peloponeſus.</note> 
                        <hi>Iſtmus</hi> or entrance, ſtands that once goodly city <hi>Corinth:</hi> which many bookes doe much mention. Further in the prouince, ſtands <hi>Lacedemon,</hi> not inferior vnto any of the reſt in antiquitie.</p>
                     <p>13 This <hi>Grecia</hi> (as is before ſaide) is vnder the <hi>Turke,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> who for money ſuffers all religions there.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF TRANSILVANIA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>TRanſiluania</hi> (ſo called, by reaſon of the great Woods <note place="margin">Limits.</note> which compaſſe it) is limited on the weſt, with <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie:</hi> and part of the Riuer <hi>Tibiſcus:</hi> on the North, with <hi>Poland,</hi> and the great mountaine <hi>Carpothus:</hi> on the Eaſt, with <hi>Moldauia:</hi> &amp; on the South, with <hi>Valachia Ciſalpina.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 The fruitfulnes of this kingdome is very much, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> horſes whoſe manes ſweepe the earth: &amp; Falchons, two of which will kill an Eagle or Swanne. There is alſo great ſtore of Mines, and in ſome riuers are found lumps of Gold, which weigh a pound weight.</p>
                     <p>3 The Inhabitants of this country are very ſtubborn, ſlothfull, and vntractable, following the religion of the <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> Greek church, reading from the right hand vnto the left, and ſwearing alwayes by <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> according vnto the olde manner of the <hi>Ethnicks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4 The chiefe citie (where the King holdeth his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) is <hi>Alha Guilia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18337:17"/>
                     <p> 5 In this Kingdome is the Prouince of <hi>Zeckland,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> after the order of the <hi>Heluetians.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6 The chiefe riuers are <hi>Saluata</hi> and <hi>Rockle,</hi> both which <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> are disburdened into <hi>Danubins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7 This <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> is gouerned by a Chriſtian <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> Prince, who once paid tribute vnto the <hi>Turke,</hi> but now doth warre againſt him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF LITVANIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>LItuania</hi> is bounded on the Weſt with <hi>Polonia,</hi> on <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the South with <hi>Podolia,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Muſcouia,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Liuonia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 There is little to be ſpoken of this Countrey, onely <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> that in it there is great ſtore of Pitch, and Timber planks, whereof they build many Ships.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of it, liue after the maner of the <hi>Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inhabitants</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 The Metropolitan Citie, where the Prince doth <note place="margin">Cities.</note> keepe his Court, is <hi>Vilna,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 This Kingdome is gouerned by a Duke, but ſubiect <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> vnto the king of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF LIVONIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>LIuonia</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with <hi>Mare Balticum,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limits.</note> or <hi>Sinus Venedicus,</hi> on the Eaſt with the riuer <hi>Narua</hi> the lake <hi>Bribas,</hi> &amp; part of <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> on the South with <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuania</hi> &amp; <hi>Pruſsia:</hi> and on the North with <hi>Sinus Finicus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 The inhabitants of this country are for the moſt part <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> al Chriſtians: and the women do think ſo wel of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that in compariſon of their owne beauties they diſcommend all others.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The riches of it are chiefly corne &amp; horſes, they haue <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> alſo in their woods wilde beaſtes, of an extraordinarie ſtrength.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18337:18"/>
                     <p n="4"> 4 The chiefe cities are firſt <hi>Riga,</hi> ſeated vpon the riuer <hi>Duina:</hi> the next is <hi>Riualia,</hi> neare vnto the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea: the laſt is <hi>Derpt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 The notedſt riuers are two, the one is the riuer <hi>Ein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke,</hi> which (at the very mouth, where it doth disburden <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> it ſelfe into the Sea,) doth fall ſuch a heigth, that it roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, making the horribleſt &amp; horrideſt noiſe, that it dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feneth the eares of the inhabitants neare adioyning, like to thoſe which dwell neare vnto the Cataracts of <hi>Nile:</hi> the other riuer is <hi>Duina.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 This Kingdome is a diſtract gouernement, ſubiect vnto many Princes, as the King of <hi>Poland, Denmark, Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> and the Emperour of <hi>Moſcouia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF SCANDIA.</head>
                     <p>1 <hi>SCandia</hi> is a Peninſula, (that is, almoſt an Iland,) inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronned <note place="margin">Limites.</note> on the North, with the frozen <hi>Ocean:</hi> on the Eaſt, with <hi>Mare Balticum, Sinus Finicus,</hi> and <hi>Sinus Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus:</hi> on the South, with <hi>Sinus Codanus:</hi> and on the Weſt, with the vaſt <hi>Ocean.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 This great cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try in the North part is very barren: but towards the South, there is great ſtore of corne, Salt, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> Horſes, and Mines, both of Siluer, Iron, and Lead.</p>
                     <p>3 The inhabitants of it are very ſtrong, peruerſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> &amp; much addicted vnto Sorceries &amp; witchcrafts.</p>
                     <p>4 This <hi>Scandia</hi> is diuided into two great Kingdoms, <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
                        <hi>Noruegia and Swetia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF NORVEGIA OR NORWAY.</head>
                     <p>5 <hi>NOruegia</hi> is bounded on the Weſt, North, &amp; South, <note place="margin">Limits.</note> with the maine <hi>Ocean,</hi> and on the Eaſt, with the <hi>Dofrine</hi> mountaines.</p>
                     <p>6 The Inhabitants of this Kingdom are ſimple men, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18337:18"/> giuen much vnto Hoſpitalitie, and abhorring Theeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or any ſuch courſes.</p>
                     <p>7 The chief riches of this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie are Cables, Maſtes, <note place="margin">Qualitie,</note> and ſuch like furniture for Shipping, there is alſo great ſtore of dried fiſh, which they eate in ſteede of bread.</p>
                     <p>8 The Metropolitane Citie is <hi>Nidroſio,</hi> there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Citie.</note> Citie called <hi>Bergen,</hi> one of the great Marte Townes of Chriſtendome.</p>
                     <p>9 This kingdom is ſubiect vnto the crowne of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gouernment.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF SWEVIA OR SWEDEN.</head>
                     <p>10 <hi>SWeuia</hi> is limited on the Weſt, with the <hi>Dofrine</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, <note place="margin">Limites.</note> and on the other parts with the Sea, vnles it be where it is ioyned vnto <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> by a little <hi>Iſtmus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>11 This Kingdome is ſo fertill and fruitefull, that it is <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> by ſome tearmed a moſt heauenly Land, abounding in ſo much prouiſion, that it is a hard thing to ſee a begger amongſt them: They digge pure Siluer out of the earth, &amp; they haue great ſtore of Wolues, which paſſing ouer a ſtraite in the Sea, are with the extremity of cold blinded.</p>
                     <p>12 The Inhabitants of this Region, are agreeable <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> much in diſpoſition &amp; quality vnto the <hi>Noruegians:</hi> they liue very long, for it is no maruel with them to ſee one an hundred and fortie yeares of age.</p>
                     <p>13 The chiefe Citie is <hi>Stockholme</hi> or <hi>Holoia,</hi> in which <note place="margin">Citie.</note> the King doth alwayes keepe his Court.</p>
                     <p>14 The Prouinces of moſt note, are firſt, <hi>Goteland (qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Good land)</hi> the next is <hi>Finneland (quaſi Fineland)</hi> in both which, is plenty almoſt of all things: the other prouinces are <hi>Bodia, Scrikfinnia</hi> &amp; <hi>Biarmia,</hi> the inhabitants of which, are much addicted vnto withcraft.</p>
                     <p>15 This Kingdome of <hi>Sweuia</hi> is ſubiect onely vnto one <note place="margin">Gouernment.</note> King, whom they call the <hi>Duke of Sweuia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18337:19"/>
                     <head>OF RVSSIA, OR MOSCOVIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>RVſsia</hi> is part in <hi>Europe,</hi> and part in <hi>Aſia,</hi> limited on <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the Weſt with <hi>Liuonia,</hi> and <hi>Scandia,</hi> on the North with <hi>Mare Glaciale,</hi> or the <hi>Frozen Ocean,</hi> on the eaſt with the Riuer <hi>Oby,</hi> the Lake of <hi>Kataio</hi> and <hi>Tartarie,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Lituania.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 The riches of this Empire wherein it chiefly excels <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> are moſt rich Furres, (as Sables, Martins, white Foxe, &amp; ſuch like.) It hath alſo in it much corne, fruits, and cattel. The ayre in theſe parts is ſo cold in the Winter, and the froſts ſo great, that if a man caſt vp water into the ayre, it wil freeze before it fall downe, &amp; many times it is ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, that if any man go abroad, he ſhal be almoſt ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled through the condenſating of his breath.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of this Countrey are very barbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> perfidious, contentious, and moſt prone vnto any contumelious behauiour: They are altogether ignorant and vnlearned, which is the occaſion that they ſay, God and their Emperour knoweth all things. The baſer ſort of people do alwayes breake the Sabboth, ſaying, that it is onely for Gentlemen to celebrate that day. They are alſo very ſuperſtitious, hauing many fooliſh ceremonies, &amp; abſurd ſolemnities, as the conſecrating of riuers once in a yere, the burying of their dead with a paire of ſhooes on their feet, and a ſtaffe in one hand, ſignifying a great iourney which they haue to goe: &amp; a letter in the other vnto S. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> for their readier admiſsion into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 The chiefe and moſt noted places of this mightie Region, are firſt <hi>Moſco,</hi> the Metropolitan citie, in which the Emperour doth continually keep his Court: The next is <hi>Pernia,</hi> in which they eate the fleſh of Stagges in ſtead of bread: And the laſt is <hi>Rhezan,</hi> in which there is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18337:19"/> ſuch plenty of graine, that the eares of corne do grow ſo thicke together, that no horſe can beate it downe, nor Larke or Quaile paſſe through it.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 The moſt famous riuers, are firſt <hi>Duina, (quaſi twag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na)</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> called ſo of two riuers which meet together. The next is <hi>Boriſtines,</hi> or <hi>Neiper,</hi> and the laſt is <hi>Tanais.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 This large Empire is onely ſubiect to the Emperor <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> of it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <div type="region">
                  <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of the European Ilands.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1 <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto haue I wandred al about the great continent of <hi>Europe,</hi> now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Ilands belonging thereunto.</p>
                  <p>2 The <hi>European Ilands</hi> are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three parts: into thoſe which are in the Weſterne Ocean, into thoſe which are in the Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean Sea, and into thoſe which are contained within the <hi>Archipellago,</hi> or <hi>Mare Aegaeum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3 The chiefe Ilands which are contained in the weſt Ocean, are ſeuen, <hi>Grocland, Groinland, Iſland, Freeſland, Ireland, Great Britaine,</hi> and the <hi>Azores.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4 <hi>Grocland</hi> is an Iland which few Geographers men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">Grocland.</note> and therfore no certaintie can be ſpoken of it.</p>
                  <p>5 <hi>Groinland (quaſi Greeneland)</hi> is a Country wherein <note place="margin">Groinland.</note>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18337:20"/> there are great ſtore of Cattell, which cauſeth Butter and Cheeſe to be very plentifull in it: the inhabitants are for the moſt part witches, dwelling in Caues and Dennes.</p>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF ISLAND.</head>
                     <p>6 <hi>ISland</hi> is an Iland very barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of graine, hauing no Trees <note place="margin">Iſland.</note> in it, vnleſſe it be Byrch and Iuniper: From this Iland, commeth the beſt Ling, called of vs <hi>Iſland Ling.</hi> In this countrie is alſo a mountaine called <hi>Heckleforte,</hi> alwayes vomiting forth flames of fire: the inhabitants of which, doe conceit thereof, a moſt peeuiſh and erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that it is Purgatorie. This Iland (as <hi>Ortelius</hi> affirms) is vnder the king of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> but others make it ſubiect vnto the <hi>Swedian</hi> Crowne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF FRISLAND.</head>
                     <p>7 <hi>FRiſlande</hi> doth abound with very great ſtore of fiſh, and <note place="margin">Friſland,</note> was wont by reaſon of the ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayling thither of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> to be called <hi>the weſterne England:</hi> this Iland is vnder the crowne of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF IRELAND.</head>
                     <p>8 <hi>IReland</hi> is a verie watriſh countrey, and full of boggs, yet <note place="margin">Ireland.</note> ſeated in a moſt temperate and pleaſant ayre, admitting no venemous thing in it, it doth moſt abounde in horſes and cattell. The inhabitants of this Kingdome are for the moſt part very beautifull, actiue, &amp; ſomewhat ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, affecting nothing ſo much as ſlothfulnes. <hi>Magi.</hi> The chiefe citie is <hi>Dubline,</hi> wherin there is an vniuerſity.</p>
                     <p>The moſt noted things of this Ile, are firſt the <hi>Lake Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> now famous for her paſt infamie, in which you may ſee the toppes of houſes and churches. The next is the <hi>Lake of Armach,</hi> into which if a long Staffe be thruſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18337:20"/> downe vnto the bottome, that parte which is in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will turne into a whetſtone, and that part which is in the mudde into Iron. <hi>Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Hybrides</hi> belong vnto this Iland, beeing in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 44. the inhabitants of which are called <hi>Redſhankes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Region belongeth vnto the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> by whom it is kept in good ſubiection.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF GREAT BRITTANIE.</head>
                     <p>9 <hi>BRIttaine</hi> is diuided into 2. partes, <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Brittaine.</note> 
                        <hi>England</hi> is ſeparated from <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the Riuer <hi>Tweede,</hi> and the Riuer <hi>Solway.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This rich Diamond ſet in the ring of the world, nurce of the moſt valiant, wiſe, and victorious men, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt with all things flouriſh: But eſpeciallie with ſuch things as this verſe that followeth, ſheweth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anglia Mons, Pons, Fons, Eccleſia, Foemina, Laua.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This part of the Ile was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in the time of King <hi>HENRY</hi> the third, <hi>Puteus inexhauſtus,</hi> a well that neuer would be drawne drie: &amp; is now tearmed by the <hi>French, a Paradiſe</hi> for wiues, a Purgatorie for <hi>Seruants,</hi> and a Hell for <hi>Horſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Scotland</hi> lyeth in the North part of this Iland: the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of which are very warlike.</p>
                     <p>The chiefe Citie is <hi>Edenbourge,</hi> neere vnto which is a fountaine that carieth an oyle, which being not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off, doth not increaſe: being taken off, doth not diminiſh.</p>
                     <p>Many other ſtrange things there are in this place, as in <hi>Lenox</hi> there is a Lake called <hi>Loumond,</hi> wherein fiſhes liue without finnes: and in which the waues are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times moſt boiſtrous in the calmeſt weather, moſt milde in the moſt tempeſtuous weather: In this Lake there is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18337:21"/> alſo a fruitfull Iland which floteth vp and downe vpon the water. In the Prouince of <hi>Coile</hi> there is a ſtone not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 13. foot in height, which if a Canon be ſhot off on the one ſide, he which is on the other cannot heare it.</p>
                     <p>The Apendices which belong vnto both <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> are firſt the <hi>Orcades,</hi> being in number 30. the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of which are great drinkers, but no drunkards. The next is the Ile of <hi>Man,</hi> wherein is the mountaine <hi>Scheſil,</hi> vpon whoſe top if any one ſtand, he may diſcerne both <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> Many other little I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands there are, all which with the reſt are ſubiect vnto the moſt mightie and puiſſant King of <hi>Great Brittainie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>INSVLAE AZORES.</head>
                     <p>10 THe <hi>Azores,</hi> or <hi>Canary Ilands,</hi> are ſeuen, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence <note place="margin">Azores.</note> commeth great ſtore of Woade, and Canarie Wines.</p>
                     <p>1 The chiefe and moſt renowned Ilands in all olde writers of the <hi>Medeterranean Sea,</hi> are nine: <hi>Inſulae Balia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Corſica, Sardinia, Scicilie, Malta, Corſyra, Iſchia, Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zinthus,</hi> and <hi>Candia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>INSVLAE BALIORES.</head>
                     <p>2 <hi>INſulae Baliores</hi> are diuided into <hi>Maiorica,</hi> in which <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inſula Bali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores.</note> 
                        <hi>Lullius</hi> that excellent Scholler liued, and into <hi>Minorica.</hi> The inhabitants of both which, are very ſtrong and expert ſlingers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>CORSICA.</head>
                     <p>3 <hi>COrſica</hi> is an Iland which doth produce Horſes of a <note place="margin">Corſica.</note> fierce nature, and Hounds of a wonderfull bignes.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18337:21"/> The Inhabitants of this Ile are verie rude and vnciuill.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>SARDINIA.</head>
                     <p>4 <hi>SArdinia</hi> (famous for the occaſion of that great warre <note place="margin">Sardinia.</note> betwixt <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Rome)</hi> is now ſubiected vnto the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The chiefe and Metropolitane citie is <hi>Cagliarie,</hi> ſeated vpon a high mountaine.</p>
                     <p>In this Countrey there is a beaſt called <hi>Mufiono,</hi> of whoſe skinne is made a Leather called <hi>Cordiuan,</hi> or as we tearme it, <hi>Spaniſh Leather.</hi> There is alſo an hearbe, which if any one eate, it will enforce him to laugh till hee dye, from whence commeth the Prouerbe, <hi>Riſus Sardonichus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>DE SCICILIA.</head>
                     <p>5 <hi>SCicilie</hi> is a land whoſe inhabitants are very good ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, <note place="margin">Scicilie.</note> deſirous much of honour, and wherein is, and haue beene many excellent Schollers, ſuch as were <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clide, Archimedes, Diodorus Siculus,</hi> and many others.</p>
                     <p>This Countrey is very fertill and fruitfull, abounding ſo much in corne, that it was once called <hi>Horeum Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum,</hi> the Store-houſe of the Romans.</p>
                     <p>In this Ile is alſo the Mountaine <hi>Aetna,</hi> at whoſe top there are (as it were) two furnaces with tunnels, out of which aſcend continually flames of fire, throwing out ſometimes ſuch ſtore of aſhes, and peeces of ſtones, that it doth greatly indaunger the Townes for many myles there about. This is the mountaine where the Poet fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to bee the ſhop of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> where the <hi>Cyclops</hi> did frame Thunder-boults for <hi>Iupiter.</hi> This is the mountain into whoſe vaſt gaping mouth <hi>Empedocles</hi> did caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And this is the mountaine where ſome of the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18337:22"/> Hereticall, and beſotted Papiſts imagine to be Purgatorie. The chiefe citie of this Ile is now <hi>Palermo,</hi> before time <hi>Siracuſa,</hi> in which liued <hi>Archimedes,</hi> that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Engine maker of the world, who, as it is written of him, would by burning Glaſſes ſet Shippes on fire ſayling in the Sea. Belonging to this are other, called the <hi>Vulcanian Ilands.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This <hi>Scicilie</hi> is now ſubiect vnto the King of <hi>Spayne.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>MALTA.</head>
                     <p>6 <hi>MAlta</hi> is moſt famous for the farre-famed order of <note place="margin">Malta.</note> the Knights of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> who haue oftentimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled and put to flight great armies of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> which haue beſieged it. This is the Countrey where Saint <hi>Paule</hi> beeing caſt vp after his ſhipwracke, had a Viper hanging on his hand, and did him no hurt. The chiefe Citie is <hi>Malta,</hi> wherein the Women are beautifull, but hate company, neuer going abroad vnleſſe they be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>CORCYCA.</head>
                     <p>7 <hi>COrcyca</hi> is an Iland flouriſhing with Wine, and Oyle. In it is alſo great ſtore of Wilde fowle, <note place="margin">Corcyca.</note> and Beaſtes, wherewith the inhabitants doe very much (with pleaſure and paſtime in chaſing them) recreate themſelues. The chiefe Citie in it, is called <hi>Corfu,</hi> wherein both men and women are excellent Swim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. This Ile is ſubiect vnto the Seigniorie of <hi>Venice,</hi> who doth defend it very well from the <hi>Turke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18337:22"/>
                     <head>ISCHIA.</head>
                     <p>8 <hi>ISchia</hi> (the chiefe of 18. Ilands lying in the Gulfe of <note place="margin">Iſchia.</note> 
                        <hi>Naples,</hi> begirt round with rockes and high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines) hath in it great ſtore of Hares, Conies, and other wilde beaſts.</p>
                     <p>The chiefe Citie is <hi>Iſchia,</hi> which in the yeare 1301. was like to be burned with a fire, that did runne along in the earth, by reaſon of the vaines of Brimſtone. In this Ile it is alſo reported that there is a Fountaine neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Promontory of Saint <hi>Angel,</hi> which is ſo hotte, that it will in a ſhort time boyle any fleſh or fiſh that is put into it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>ZAZINTHVS.</head>
                     <p>9 <hi>ZAzinthus</hi> is a land where Engliſh Merchants doe <note place="margin">Zazinthus.</note> very much trafficke, for the extraordinary ſtore of Currants which are there. In this Ile the inhabitants do ſpeake Greeke, and are ſubiect vnto the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>CANDIA.</head>
                     <p>10 <hi>CAndie</hi> is an Iland famoſed by the intricate Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borinth <note place="margin">Creete.</note> which was in it, built by <hi>Dedalus:</hi> and which <hi>Theſeus</hi> entred, and killed the <hi>Minataurs,</hi> which were kept in it, by the helpe of <hi>Ariadne,</hi> who gaue him a bottome of threed to guide him.</p>
                     <p>In this Ile there is very much Suger-Candie, &amp; Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadine, in ſuch plentie, that there is yearely tranſported into other countries 12000. Buts.</p>
                     <p>The Inhabitants of this place doe not affect labour, neuer vſing any manfull exerciſe, but giuen vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vices, eſpecially lying: of which the Prouerbe, <hi>Cretenſe Mendarium, &amp; Cretiſandum eſt cum Cretenſibus.</hi>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18337:23"/> And <hi>Epiminides</hi> the heathen Poet noteth of them, that they are alwayes great lyers, dull beaſts, and ſlow bellies.</p>
                     <p>The chiefe citie of it is <hi>Candie,</hi> inhabited much with the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>Of the Ilands in the Aegean Sea.</head>
                  <p>1 THe Ilands in the Aegean Sea, are all ſubiect vnto the tyrannicall <hi>Turke,</hi> and are diuided either into the <hi>Cyclades,</hi> which are fiftie in number, lying towards the South; or into the <hi>Sporades,</hi> which are very many, lying towards the North.</p>
                  <p>2 Of the <hi>Cyclades</hi> little can be ſpoken, only that in the <note place="margin">Cyclades.</note> Iland <hi>Delos</hi> ſtood the famous Oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny writers made mention of: And that in <hi>Ithaca</hi> valiant <hi>Vliſſes</hi> was borne.</p>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>SPORADES.</head>
                     <p>3 THe <hi>Sporades</hi> are many, whereof the chiefe are firſt, <note place="margin">Sporades.</note> 
                        <hi>Euboia,</hi> at whoſe bankes the Sea doth ebbe &amp; flow ſeuen times in a day: which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> on a time viewing, and being not able to giue a naturall reaſon for it, deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately threw himſelf into it. The next is <hi>Sciros,</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Achilles.</hi> Then <hi>Chios,</hi> the Countrey of the great Phyſitian <hi>Hypocrates.</hi> And the laſt of any note is <hi>Pathmos,</hi> the Iland where Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> liued in baniſhment, and in which there is a dead hand, the nailes of it ſtill growing, which as the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſay, was the hand of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> But the <hi>Turkes</hi> affirme it to be the hand of one of their Prophets.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18337:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Africa.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto haue I remained within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Europe,</hi> now ſucceedeth <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Africa,</hi> (ſo called in Greeke of <hi>a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; phrica,</hi> a place without coldneſſe) is limited on the Weſt with the <hi>Atlanticke Ocean,</hi> on the North with <hi>Mare Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneum,</hi> and on the South with the <hi>Aethyopicke</hi> waues, and on the Eaſt with the <hi>Red Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 This great part of the world, is for the moſt part <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> full of Deſarts, very dry and ſandy, hauing few Riuers, which is a great occaſion that ſome parts are not habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It is alſo full of all ſtrange beaſtes, as Elephants, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Leopards, Hyppopotomos, Crocadiles, and ſuch like: which cauſed this ſaying of <hi>Plinie, Africa aliquid ſemper opportat Noui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of it, are generally very blacke, of <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> countenance rude, barbarous, and of vnciuil behauiour, addicted to all ſorts of religion, of <hi>Gentiles, Iewes, Turkes, Chriſtians,</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The famous Riuers of this part, are firſt, <hi>Nilus,</hi> which <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> ſpringeth out of the Mountaines of the Moone, as <hi>Ptol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomie</hi> affirmes: but (as <hi>Heroditus</hi> ſayes) out of a Lake cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Strabo.</hi> The other riuers are <hi>Niger, Fluuius, Senega, Cambra, Naire, Cuama,</hi> and <hi>Spiritus ſancti.</hi> There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mountaine in <hi>Africa,</hi> called the <hi>Mountaine Atlas,</hi> from whence (as <hi>Hondius</hi> writeth in his Mappes) moſt of the Riuers haue their beginning.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18337:24"/>
               <p n="5"> The chiefe parts of <hi>Africa</hi> are ſeuen: <hi>Barbarie,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> which is comprehended <hi>Mauritania, Tingitana,</hi> and <hi>Caeſarienſis, Ptolamt: Numedia,</hi> or <hi>Benedulgerid: Libia,</hi> or <hi>Sarra: Terra Nigritarum: Aethtopia ſuperior,</hi> or the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the <hi>Abiſines: Aethiopia inferior,</hi> and <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>OF BARBARIE.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>BArbarie</hi> is enuironed on the Weſt with the <hi>Atlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanticke</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> 
                     <hi>Sea,</hi> on the North with <hi>Mare Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum,</hi> on the South with the great Mountaine <hi>Atlas,</hi> and on the Eaſt with <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 This Region doth abound with Oranges, Dates, <note place="margin">Qualitis.</note> Oliues, Figges, and a certain kind of Goate, whoſe haire doth make a ſtuffe as fine as ſilke.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of this countrey are very faithfull <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> in their promiſes, ambitious, greedy of wealth, and moſt iealous of their wiues.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The chiefe Prouinces of this great kingdome, are <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                     <hi>Morocco, Fez, Tremiſen, Tunis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Barca Marmarica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Morocco,</hi> wherin the chiefe citie is <hi>Morocco,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of which doth alwaies keepe their beards ſhaued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be married. There is alſo in this Prouince the mountaine <hi>Halemo,</hi> in which there is ſo much gold, that the inhabitants are at continuall ſtrife for it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 The next Prouince is <hi>Fez,</hi> the chiefe &amp; Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan citie of which, is called <hi>Fez,</hi> beeing of a wonderfull greatnes, hauing in it 700. churches, one among the reſt being of a mile &amp; halfe in compaſſe. In this citie are alſo two Colledges, wherein liue many Schollers.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 The next prouince is <hi>Tremiſen,</hi> whoſe Metropolitan citie is <hi>Tremiſen,</hi> in it is alſo <hi>Algera,</hi> a great receptacle for Pirats.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 The next is <hi>Tunis,</hi> in which is <hi>Bona,</hi> where S. <hi>Agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18337:24"/> was Biſhop, and <hi>Hippo</hi> where he was borne. The chiefe and Metropolitan city is <hi>Tunis,</hi> not farre from the ruines of old <hi>Carthage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9 The laſt Prouince is <hi>Barca Marmarica,</hi> full of great ſandy places, and in which Ilands is the Temple of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Hammon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10 This Kingdome of <hi>Barbarie,</hi> is a diſtracted gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> 
                     <hi>Fez</hi> and <hi>Morocco</hi> being vnder the <hi>Xeriffe,</hi> and the other Prouinces vnder the <hi>Turkes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>OF NVMIDIA.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>NVmidia</hi> is bounded on the Weſt with <hi>Mare Atlanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> on the North with the Mountaine <hi>Atlas,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and on the South with the Deſarts of <hi>Libia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 This countrey hath in it great plenty of Dates, and <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> the ayre is ſo holeſome, that it admitteth neither Poxe nor Plague in it, but cureth any one that hath it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The inhabitants are oftentimes blinded, by reaſon <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> of the vnreaſonable ſtore of ſand which is there, much of it being carried and blowed with the winde. They are alſo much addicted vnto Poetry.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The gouernment of this Region, is not vnder any <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> ſole King, but ſubiect vnto many free Gouernors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>Of Libia, or Sarra.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>LIbia</hi> is limited on the Weſt with <hi>Gualata,</hi> on the Eaſt <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> with <hi>Gaoga,</hi> on the North with <hi>Numidia,</hi> and on the South with the kingdome of the <hi>Negroes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The inhabitants of this countrey are baſe minded, <note place="margin">Inhabitants</note> ill nurturde, and great theeues: they liue not ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any lawes. In this place were two of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> who propheſied of the comming of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18337:25"/>
                  <p n="3"> 3 This kingdome is ful of Deſarts, of which the chief are <hi>Zanaga, Zueziga, Tarſa, Lempia, and Berdoa.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>Of the Kingdome of the Nigers.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 THe Kingdome of the <hi>Nigers</hi> is bounded on the <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> Weſt with the <hi>Atlanticke Sea,</hi> on the Eaſt with the Kingdome of the <hi>Abiſsines,</hi> on the South with <hi>Manicon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Libia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The inhabitants of this Countrey are moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> people, Gentiles, and free from the Plague or Poxe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 In this great and large kingdome there are twentie <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> fiue Prouinces, among which theſe things are chiefly to be noted. Firſt is the Riuer <hi>Niger,</hi> which with a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vndation encreaſing from the 15. of Iune, vntill 40. daies after, doth ouerflow a great part of the land: and in the like time it doth decreaſe againe. The next is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Canaga,</hi> wherein the King hath no certaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes, but onely what his Nobles giue him. The next is <hi>Tombutum,</hi> where the king doth entertain a great company of learned men, and where inhabitants doe ſpend their time in dauncing and ſinging. The laſt is <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum,</hi> where the people haue neither proper names, children, nor wiues.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 This great Kingdome of the <hi>Nigers</hi> is gouerned by foure Kings: the King of <hi>Tombutum, Bornum, Goaga,</hi> and <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> the King of <hi>Gualatum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>Of the Kingdome of the Abiſsines.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 THe Kingdome of the <hi>Abiſsines</hi> is limited on the North with <hi>Aegypt,</hi> on the South with the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> of the Moone, on the Eaſt with the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and on the Weſt with <hi>Manicongo,</hi> and the Kingdome of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18337:25"/>
                  <p n="2"> 2 This countrey is chiefly inricht with Oranges, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> and Citrens, which grow of themſelues. There is alſo great ſtore of Barley, Suger, and Hony.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of this Nation, are generally vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> baſe, idle: the better ſort of them attyring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the skinnes of Lions, Tigres, and Linces. They feare a Smith as much as a Diuell: and at meate neuer vſe a table, cloth, nor napkin. They alwayes (in any matter) ſweare by the life of the King, whome they neuer ſee but thriſe in a yeare, which is on Chriſtmas, Eaſter, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Rood day. They neuer baptiſe their children before the fortieth day, and alſo circumciſe both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 This great Kingdome is gouerned by <hi>Prester Iohn,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> who hath vnder him 70. Kings; and whoſe colour is white, his ſubiects being all blacke. He draweth his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree from <hi>Melecke,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Salamon,</hi> and Queene of the South.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>Of Ethiopia inferiour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>EThiopia inferior,</hi> is euery where begirt with the Sea, <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> vnleſſe it be towards the North, where it is boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from <hi>Ethiopia ſuperior,</hi> with the Mountaines of the Moone.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The inhabitants of this Country are very Sauage, <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> cruell, and for the moſt part great Idolaters, ſo much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning Chriſtianitie, that in the Prouince of <hi>Douos,</hi> no man can marry vntill he hath killed twelue Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The Prouinces of this Region, are vnder fiue free <note place="margin">Prouinces &amp; Gouernment.</note> Kngs: The king of <hi>Zanzibar, Monomotapa, Manicongo, Ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> and <hi>Carfraria:</hi> of all which little can be ſpoken, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that in the <hi>Monomotapa,</hi> there are <hi>Amozons,</hi> which are more valiant then the men, and that the King thereof
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18337:26"/> doth keepe for his guard 200. Maſtiffe dogges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="territory">
                  <head>OF AEGYPT.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>EGypt</hi> is limited on the Weſt with <hi>Barbarie,</hi> on the <note place="margin">Bounds.</note> South with <hi>Aethiopia ſuperior,</hi> on the Eaſt with the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> or <hi>Sinus Arabicus,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Mare Mediterraneum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 As concerning the fruitfulneſſe of this Countrey, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> theſe two verſes which follow, ſhall and doe ſufficiently make it knowne.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Terra ſuis contenta bonis, non Indiga Mercis aut Iouis. </l>
                     <l>In ſolo tanta eſt fiducia Nilo.</l>
                     <note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
                  </q>
                  <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of this Kingdome are very actiue, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> liberall, giuen vnto feaſting, ſomewhat ſuperſtitious, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them Chriſtians, but the greater part Mahumeta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The chiefe cities are two, the firſt is <hi>Caire,</hi> once cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Cities.</note> 
                     <hi>Memphis,</hi> neere vnto which ſtands the <hi>Piramides</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> one of the ſeuen wonders of the worlde. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which was built by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and wherein was the moſt famous Library of the world. This was the place alſo, where <hi>Ptolomie</hi> tooke all his obſeruations.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 In this Kingdome was inuented Aſtronomie, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, <note place="margin">Inuentions.</note> and writing on paper: It was called <hi>Papirus,</hi> of the thing which it was made of, and in Latine <hi>Charta,</hi> of the place where it was inuented. <hi>Hond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 The gouernment of this once famous Region, was heretofore vnder Kings, whom they commonly called <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> 
                     <hi>Pharoes:</hi> but now belongeth to the trueth abhorring <hi>Turke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18337:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>Of the chiefe Ilands in Africa.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus much of the continent of <hi>Africa:</hi> now will I knit vnto it the deſcription of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The Ilands of <hi>Africa</hi> are diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> two parts: into thoſe which are in the <hi>Atlanticke Sea,</hi> and into thoſe which are in the <hi>Aethiopicke Ocean.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thoſe Ilands which are in the <hi>Atlantick Sea</hi> of note, are onely the <hi>Canarie Ilands,</hi> the <hi>Gorgades,</hi> and the Iland of S. <hi>Thomas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The <hi>Canarie,</hi> or Fortunate Ilands, are 7. of which the <note place="margin">Canarie.</note> chiefe is <hi>Madera,</hi> wherein there is great ſtore of Suger, and Canary Wine. There is another, which is called <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariffa,</hi> wherein is a mountaine ſo high, that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants haue all their freſh water from a cloude that drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth there very faſt, hanging about a tree.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The <hi>Gorgades are</hi> nine, all which are full of Goates, <note place="margin">Gorgades.</note> and ſubiect vnto the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 The Iland of Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> lyeth directly vnder the <hi>Aequator,</hi> it is very plentifull of Suger, and a place vnto which the <hi>Portugals</hi> do much reſort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>Of the Ilands in the Aethiopicke Sea.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 THe Ilands of the <hi>Aethiopicke Ocean,</hi> are but two of <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> any fame: <hi>Magdagaſcar,</hi> and <hi>Zocotara.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Magdagaſcar,</hi> or the Iland of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> is a countrey <note place="margin">Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſcar.</note> whoſe inhabitants are very cruell and barbarous,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18337:27"/> and in which there are great ſtore of Elephants.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Zocotara</hi> is an Iland, in which the people are all <note place="margin">Zocotara.</note> Chriſtians, and dwell in Caues, and great holes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>Of Aſia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto haue I ſcorcht my ſelfe in the heate of <hi>Africa,</hi> now therefore of the temperate Continent of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Aſia</hi> is in euery place begirt with the Sea, vnleſſe it be towards the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne <note place="margin">Limits.</note> parts, where it is limited from <hi>Europe</hi> with the Riuer <hi>Tanais,</hi> and a line directly drawne vp vnto the Port of Saint <hi>Nicholas.</hi> And from <hi>Africa</hi> with that <hi>Iſtmus,</hi> betwixt the Arabick Gulfe, and the Mediterranean Sea.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 This part of the world is farre more famous then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other: For here was the place where the Monarkes of the <hi>Medes, Perſians, Babilonians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſsirians</hi> flouriſhed. Here was the place in which all the actes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the olde Teſtament, and almoſt in the new, were accompliſhed. And here was, and is, the place where the Myracles of our Sauiour were done, for euer to be celebrated.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The fruitfulneſſe of this great Continent is very <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> much, for it doth containe within it, almoſt plentie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The inhabitants of it, are generally very wittie, for <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> from hence ſprang all the Sciences which the Greekes haue learned of the Hebrewes.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18337:27"/>
                  <p n="5"> 5 The chiefe Riuers of <hi>Aſia,</hi> are <hi>Iaxartes, Euphrates, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Riuers</note> 
                     <hi>Indus,</hi> and <hi>Ganges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 Two other things there are in this part worthy to be noted: Firſt, is the Mountaine <hi>Taurus,</hi> which diuides whole <hi>Aſia</hi> into two parts, being in length 5625. miles, &amp; in breadth 375. Next, is <hi>Mare Caſpium,</hi> a Sea which hath no entercourſe with any part of the Ocean.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 This <hi>Aſia</hi> is diuided into ſixe great Gouernements, <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> into that of <hi>Moſcouia</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> which I haue before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: Into <hi>Turcia Aſiana, Tartarie, Perſia, India,</hi> &amp; <hi>China.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF TVRCIA ASIANA.</head>
                     <p>1 <hi>VNder the</hi> Turkes <hi>Empire in</hi> Aſia, <hi>are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> Natolia, <hi>or</hi> Aſia minor: Turcomania, Syria, <hi>or</hi> Paleſtina: <hi>and</hi> Arabia.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF NATOLIA.</head>
                     <p>2 <hi>NAtolia,</hi> or <hi>Aſia minor,</hi> is limited on the Weſt with <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> on the South with the Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Sea, on the Eaſt with the Riuer <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Pontus Euxinus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3 This Countrey is very fruitfull and temperat, but <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> by reaſon of the <hi>Turkes</hi> tyranny, it lyeth very waſte, and not inhabited. For in it may be ſeene the ruines of 4000. Townes and Cities.</p>
                     <p>4 The inhabitants are moſt idle, lazy, and in religion <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> Mahumetans. Once they were all Chriſtians, for with them were the ſeuen churches, which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chalips did write vnto.</p>
                     <p>5 The chiefe Prouinces of <hi>Natolia</hi> are 8, <hi>Pontus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinia: Aſia propria,</hi> or <hi>Sarrum: Licia, Pamphilia, Galatia,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and <hi>Cylicia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6 In <hi>Pontus</hi> and <hi>Bithinia,</hi> there are two famous cities, <note place="margin">Pontus &amp; Bithinia.</note>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18337:28"/> the one called <hi>Nice,</hi> where the firſt generall Councell was held: the other <hi>Chalcedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> where the fourth was held. Theſe Prouinces were once gouerned by <hi>Mithridates,</hi> who was the firſt finder out of Metridate.</p>
                     <p>7 In <hi>Aſia Propria,</hi> or <hi>Sarcum,</hi> there are many things <note place="margin">Aſia propria</note> worthy the obſeruation: as firſt, <hi>Phrigia maior,</hi> of which <hi>Midas</hi> was King: next <hi>Phrigia minor,</hi> wherein are to be ſeene the ruines of olde <hi>Troy,</hi> and in which ſtands <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> where <hi>Gallen,</hi> that famous Phyſitian was borne. In this country alſo liued <hi>Gordius,</hi> who knit the knot, which for the intricateneſſe therof was called <hi>Nodus Gordianus.</hi> The next is <hi>Lidia,</hi> in which liued rich King <hi>Craeſſus.</hi> The next is <hi>Ionia,</hi> wherein ſtands that famous citie <hi>Epheſus,</hi> moſt renowned for the great Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> which was in it, accounted to bee one of the wonders of the world. This is alſo one of the ſeuen Cities which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reuelation wrote vnto, and vnto which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> did direct one of his Epiſtles. In this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince is alſo <hi>Smirna,</hi> an other of the ſeuen Cities, and in which <hi>Policarpus</hi> (that was Biſhoppe there) liued, who ſometimes had beene Scholler vnto Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt. The next, is <hi>Halicarnaſſus,</hi> wherein <hi>Dioniſius</hi> and <hi>Heroditus,</hi> thoſe famous Hiſtoriographers liued. The laſt of any fame, is the riuer <hi>Meandrus,</hi> which hath 600. turnings.</p>
                     <p>8 In <hi>Licia</hi> little is to be noted, onely that there ſtand <note place="margin">Licia.</note> ſome ruines of the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and that S. <hi>Nicholas</hi> liued there.</p>
                     <p>9 In <hi>Pamphilia</hi> ſtands the Citie of <hi>Seleucia,</hi> built <note place="margin">Pamphilia.</note> by <hi>Seleucus,</hi> one of the foure great ſucceſſours of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>10 In <hi>Galatia</hi> were the people vnto whome Saint <note place="margin">Galatia.</note> 
                        <hi>Paule</hi> writ one of his Epiſtles: And this alſo is one of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18337:28"/> the Prouinces, where the <hi>Iewes</hi> were diſperſed.</p>
                     <p>11 In <hi>Capadocia</hi> is that flouriſhing Citie of <hi>Trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zond,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Capadocia.</note> which in times paſt was a Citie Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
                     <p>12 In <hi>Cilicia</hi> is the Citie <hi>Tarſus,</hi> where S. <hi>Paule</hi> was <note place="margin">Cilicia.</note> borne, &amp; vnto which <hi>Ionas</hi> fled, when hee was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to goe vnto <hi>Niniuie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>13 The laſt Prouince is <hi>Armenia minor,</hi> in which there <note place="margin">Armenia the leſſe.</note> is great ſtore of Oyle, and excellent Wine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF TVRCOMANIA.</head>
                     <p>14 <hi>TVrcomania,</hi> or <hi>Armenia maior,</hi> is bounded on the <note place="margin">Limites.</note> Weſt with the Riuer <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and <hi>Pontus Euxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> on the South with <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Media,</hi> and <hi>Mare Caſpium,</hi> and on the North with part of <hi>Tartaria.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>15 The inhabitants of this Region, are great rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <note place="margin">Inhabitants</note> liuing after the manner of the baſeſt ſort of Tartars, that is, vnder tents, going from one place vnto another in companies.</p>
                     <p>16 The chiefe Prouinces are two, the firſt is <hi>Georgia,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> ſeated on the bankes of the Caſpian Sea, wherein the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants do chiefly worſhip Saint <hi>George:</hi> The other is <hi>Colchus,</hi> from whence <hi>Iaſon</hi> did ſetch the Golden Fleece.</p>
                     <p>17 In this <hi>Turcomania,</hi> the thing which is moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, is, that the Arke of <hi>Noe</hi> did firſt reſt it ſelfe vpon the Mountaines of <hi>Armenia,</hi> now called <hi>Nohae montes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>Of Syria, or Paleſtina.</head>
                     <p>18 <hi>SYria, Paleſtine,</hi> or the <hi>Holy land,</hi> is limited on the <note place="margin">Limits.</note> Weſt with <hi>Mare Mediterraneum:</hi> on the South
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18337:29"/> with <hi>Arabia,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and on the North with the mountaine <hi>Libanus.</hi> This countrey is in compaſſe 200. miles.</p>
                     <p>19 The inhabitants of it were once ſo many, that it did <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> containe in it 30. Kings: and when <hi>Dauid</hi> did command the people to be numbred, there were found 1300000. fighting men. But at this time there are very few, &amp; thoſe Chriſtians of euery ſect, and Saracens.</p>
                     <p>20 The fruitfulneſſe of this Kingdome doth chiefly <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> conſiſt of Wines, whoſe Grapes do grow in ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that they are gathered thrice in a yeare: They haue alſo great ſtore of Apples, and Lemons.</p>
                     <p>21 The Prouinces which this Region is diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> are foure, <hi>Gallilie, Samaria, Iudaea,</hi> and <hi>Idumea.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>22 <hi>Gallily</hi> is diuided into the higher and lower. In the <note place="margin">Gallilie.</note> higher is <hi>Phinicia,</hi> vnder which is comprehended <hi>Tire</hi> &amp; <hi>Sidon.</hi> In the lower is <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where Chriſt was borne: and in it is alſo the Mountaine <hi>Tabor,</hi> where our Sauiour was transfigured.</p>
                     <p>23 In the Prouince of <hi>Samaria,</hi> ſtood that great city of <note place="margin">Samaria.</note> 
                        <hi>Samaria,</hi> the ruines of which are yet to be ſeene: and not farre from thence the citie <hi>Sichar,</hi> where Chriſt deſired water of a certaine woman.</p>
                     <p>24 In the Prouince of <hi>Iudaea</hi> ſtood the once famous <note place="margin">Iudaea.</note> Citie of the world, called <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where the Sepulchre of Chriſt is to be ſeene: and not farre from thence ſtood <hi>Bethlaem,</hi> where he was borne. There is alſo in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, an hearbe called <hi>Bachara,</hi> whoſe colour is like vnto a flame, and in the euening ſhineth like vnto a Sunne-beame, which if any one come to plucke it vp, it wil wag from him, vntill the vrine of a woman bee ſprinkled on it. <hi>Ioſephus de Bello Iudaico, Lib.</hi> 7.</p>
                     <p>25 The chiefe Riuers and Lakes of theſe Prouinces, <note place="margin">Riue</note>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18337:29"/> are foure. The firſt is <hi>Iordan,</hi> which ſpringeth out of the Mountaine <hi>Libanus,</hi> ſo called of <hi>Ior</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> two riuers which meete together. The ſecond is the Lake of <hi>Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</hi> The third is the Lake of <hi>Genazareth,</hi> or <hi>Tiberia,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for our Sauiours ſailing in it. The fourth and laſt, is <hi>Mare Mortuum,</hi> or the Dead Sea, into which <hi>Iordan</hi> is disburdened. At the top of this Lake ſwimmeth Pitch and Brimſtone, from whence reaketh ſuch a ſtinking miſt, that it killeth all the birds that flye ouer it, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Apples that grow by it, being faire in ſhew, very rotten. Moreouer, the water is of that nature, that if an Oxe were throwne in with his feete bound, hee will not ſinke. <hi>Ioſephus Solinus,</hi> 48. <hi>Chap.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF ARABIA.</head>
                     <p>26 <hi>ARabia</hi> is encompaſt on the Weſt with the Red Sea, <note place="margin">Limites.</note> on the South with the maine Ocean, on the Eaſt with <hi>Sinus Perſicus,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>27 It is diuided into three parts, into <hi>Arabia Deſerta,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
                        <hi>Petroſa,</hi> and <hi>Foelix.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>28 In <hi>Arabia Deſerta</hi> nothing is worth the obſeruing, but that it was the place where God did keepe the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſraell</hi> for the ſpace of 40. yeares, feeding them with Manna from heauen.</p>
                     <p>29 Of <hi>Arabia Petroſa,</hi> little can be ſpoken, onely that there ſtands the Mountaine <hi>Sinay,</hi> where God gaue the Tables of the Law vnto <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>30 <hi>Arabia Foelix,</hi> is one of the moſt fruitfulleſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in the world, hauing in it Franchincenſe, mirrhe, &amp; moſt pretious Balmes, which are in no other places to be found.</p>
                     <p>31 The chiefe Citie is <hi>Mediua,</hi> where <hi>Mahumet</hi> was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18337:30"/> intombed in an yron Coffin, which being carried into a Temple, the roofe whereof was made of Adamant, is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted vnto the toppe of the Vault, and there hangeth, being ſupported by nothing.</p>
                     <p>32 The inhabitants of this Region, are ſuperſtitious, <note place="margin">Inhabitants</note> and in all their doings very vnconſtant. They are in their Religion Mahometans. And as we reckon our time fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yeare of our Lord, ſo they from the time of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whoſe comming they haue long expected: ſaying, there were three great Prophets, <hi>Moſes, Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Mahomet.</hi> And as the Doctrine of <hi>Moſes</hi> was bettered by Chriſt, ſo was the Doctrine of Chriſt mended by <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus much concerning the <hi>Turkes</hi> Dominions in <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF TARTARIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>TArtarie</hi> is limited on the North with the <hi>Scithian</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limites.</note> Sea, on the Eaſt with the Eaſt Ocean, on the South with the <hi>Indies,</hi> and the Wall of <hi>China,</hi> and on the Weſt with <hi>Moſcouia,</hi> and <hi>Sarmatia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 The inhabitants of this Countrey are of a meane <note place="margin">Inuentions.</note> ſtature, large in the ſhoulders, broad in the face, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing flat Noſes, and long Beardes. They marrie as many wiues as they will, liuing abroad in Tents made of the skinnes of Beaſtes: thinking it a great vnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if they remaine in one place longer then the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures haue meate for their Cattell. They eate the raw fleſh of Horſes, onely a little ſcorcht in the Sunne, not reſpecting how they were killed, or what diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they died of. When they thirſt, they let their Horſes blood, and then ſucke till they bee ſatisfied. They cannot abide Hogges fleſh. And for their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18337:30"/> they are both <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Saracens.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The chiefe Prouinces of <hi>Tartarie</hi> are fiue, <hi>Tartaria</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>minor, Tartaria Aſiatica, Tartaria Antiqua, Zagathay,</hi> or <hi>Scithia intra Imaum montem, Cathaia,</hi> or <hi>Scithia extra Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um montem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 In <hi>Tartarie</hi> the leſſe, is <hi>Horda Precopenſium,</hi> which liue in the fieldes about <hi>Pontus Euxinus, Meotis Palus,</hi> and about <hi>Taurica Cherſoneſus.</hi> Theſe are all ſubiect vnto the <hi>Turke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 In <hi>Tartaria Aſiatica,</hi> lying betweene the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Tanays,</hi> and the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, are many <hi>Hordes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the which the cheife are <hi>Horda Astinchanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> and <hi>Caſanenſis,</hi> both beeing ſubiect vnto the <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couite.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 In <hi>Tartaria Antiqua,</hi> are the Kingdomes of <hi>Gogge,</hi> and <hi>Magogge,</hi> from whence the <hi>Tartares</hi> firſt had their beginning, and from whence came King <hi>Tabor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7 In <hi>Zargathay,</hi> or <hi>Scithia intra Imaum montem,</hi> is <hi>Samarchand,</hi> lying betweene the Riuer <hi>Iaxartes</hi> and <hi>Oxus,</hi> where <hi>Tamburline</hi> liued, that went into the field againſt <hi>Baiazeth</hi> the Turke, with ſeuen hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Tartares.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The chiefe and Metropolitane Citie of it is <hi>Richend,</hi> a place of great Trafficke.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 In <hi>Cathayo,</hi> or <hi>Scithia extra Imaum montem,</hi> is the Citie of <hi>Cambalowe,</hi> the chiefe ſeate of the Great <hi>Cham,</hi> beeing in compaſſe twenty foure miles. In this part alſo is the mountaine <hi>Altay,</hi> where they intombe alwayes the bodie of their Great <hi>Cham,</hi> which whyle they carrie the dead corpes vnto the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, they kill all they meete, and bid them goe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18337:31"/> and ſerue their Maiſter in another world.</p>
                     <p n="9">9 This part of <hi>Tartarie</hi> or <hi>Carthayo extra Imaum mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> is gouerned onely by one, who is called the Great <hi>Cham,</hi> whoſe word ſtands for a lawe, and is titled of his ſubiects, <hi>Filius Dei, Vmbra Dei, &amp; Anima Dei.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF PERSIA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>PErſia</hi> is limited on the Weſt with <hi>Sinus Perſicus,</hi> on <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the North with <hi>Mare Caſpium,</hi> and the riuer <hi>Oxus,</hi> on the South with the maine Ocean, and on the Eaſt with <hi>Indus Fluius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 This mightie Region hath in it great ſtore of met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> and pretious ſtones, as much flouriſhing in faire Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and Lakes, as poore in fruits, hauing no trees but onely Palmes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of this Kingdome are very cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> affecting hoſpitalitie, addicted much vnto Poetry and Phyſicke, and among whom Nobilitie is highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed. They are of Religion for the moſt part Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, <note place="margin">Religion.</note> but ſuch as the Turkes call Sciſmatickes.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 The Prouinces of this great Gouernement are ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> 
                        <hi>Meſopotamia, Aſsiria, Chaldaea, Suſiana, Farſus, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania, Parthia, Hyrcania, Gedroſia, Drangiana, Aria, Margi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana, Aracoſia, Parapomiſſus, and Brachana.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5 <hi>Meſopotamia, quaſi meſos potamos,</hi> lieth betweene the <note place="margin">Meſopotam.</note> riuer <hi>Tigris</hi> and <hi>Euphrates,</hi> in which, ſome thinke, ſtood the terreſtiall <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and that from hence came the wiſe men, which brought preſents vnto Chriſt, beeing guided by a ſtarre. This countrey is now ſubiect vnto the <hi>Turke.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6 <hi>Aſsiria</hi> is very famous for the great Citie <hi>Niniuie,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Aſſiria.</note> which ſtood in it, vnto which <hi>Ionas</hi> was commanded by God to go and preach. This is alſo ſubiect vnto the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:18337:31"/>
                     <p n="7"> 7 <hi>Chaldaea</hi> is renowned for that great citie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Chaldaea.</note> one of the ſeuen wonders of the world, &amp; from whence came the confuſion of tongues. Here was that famous <hi>Erithea,</hi> the fift <hi>Sybil,</hi> that propheſied of the comming of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 Of the other Prouinces nothing I finde worth the noting, and the refore omit them.</p>
                     <p n="9">9 The chiefe and Metropolitane Citie, is <hi>Perſepolis,</hi> ſeated vpon the Riuer <hi>Bindimire.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10 This Kingdome of <hi>Perſia</hi> is gouerned by one, <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> whom they call the <hi>Sophy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>Of the Eaſt Indies.</head>
                     <p>1 <hi>INdia Orientalis,</hi> or the Eaſt Indies, is bounded on the <note place="margin">Limits.</note> Weſt with the riuer <hi>Indus,</hi> on the North with the Mountaine <hi>Taurus,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>China,</hi> and on the South with the maine Ocean.</p>
                     <p>2 This country doth exceed any other in fruit, which is <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> gathered there twiſe in a yere. There are alſo ſuch a huge kind of Maſtiffe Dogges, that for ſtrength they are able to contend with Lions. There are great ſtore of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, white Apes, Camels, Dragons, and an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of Serpents, which are as big as any man, the inhabitants eating them as commonly as we do any meate.</p>
                     <p>3 The inhabitants are a mixt ſort of people, beeing <note place="margin">Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti.</note> Perſians, Scithians, Arabians, Hebrewes, &amp; ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. They are commonly ingenious, much inclined vnto all Sciences. They adore one ſole God, which they paint with three heads, but cannot giue a reaſon for it.</p>
                     <p>4 <hi>India</hi> is diuided into two parts, <hi>India infra Gangem,</hi> and <hi>India extra Gangem.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:18337:32"/>
                     <head>De India within Ganges.</head>
                     <p>5 <hi>INdia intra Gangem,</hi> is inuironed on the Weſt with the <note place="margin">Limits.</note> riuer <hi>Indus,</hi> on the South with the maine Ocean, on Eaſt with <hi>Sinus Bengala,</hi> and the Riuer <hi>Ganges,</hi> and on the North with part of the Mountaine <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6 This part is diuided into fortie ſeuen Kingdoms, <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> among which there are onely fiue of any note, <hi>Cambaia, Decan, Malabar, Narſinga, and Delly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7 In the Kingdome of <hi>Cambaia,</hi> the people are ſo <note place="margin">Cambaia.</note> ceremonious and ſuperſtitious, that they will not eate any thing that hath had life in it. They are great Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, liuing in due obſeruance of their King, who is a moſt valiant Prince. The chiefe Citie is <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baia,</hi> wherein if any one dye, they preſently burne his body, that it may diſſolue into his proper elements. <hi>Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius in tabulis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>8 <hi>Decan</hi> is a Kingdome made famous by the Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls, <note place="margin">Decan.</note> which lye continually in the great Citie of <hi>Goa.</hi> Not farre from this citie is a place, which if the hornes of any Beaſt bee caſt, they will take roote and grow vp out of the ground. <hi>Hugo a Linſchotten in cap.</hi> 61. of the deſcription of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>9 In <hi>Malabar</hi> ſtands the Citie <hi>Calicute,</hi> the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants <note place="margin">Malabar.</note> of which doe worſhippe the Diuell: the King of it is titled by his ſubiects <hi>Samori,</hi> which ſignifieth God on earth. They are very skilfull Souldiours, vſing when they goe vnto Warre, to tye vnto the hilts of their Swordes Shingles of Copper, or Siluer, the ſound whereof in ſteed of Trumpets and Drummes, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them vnto fight. By the lawe of their Countrey they may not marry, but are allowed women in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18337:32"/>
                     <p> 10 <hi>Narſinga,</hi> is a land fruitfull in euery thing, vnleſſe <note place="margin">Narſinga.</note> it bee Horſes. The chiefe Citie in it is <hi>Biſnagar,</hi> in which the people when they dye are burned: and if they were marryed, their wiues doe come and leape into the fire, willing to dye with them.</p>
                     <p>11 The laſt is the Kingdome of <hi>Delly;</hi> in which the <note place="margin">Delly.</note> chiefe and Metropolitane Citie is <hi>Delly,</hi> where the great <hi>Mogor</hi> doth alwayes keepe his Court.</p>
                     <p>12 The gouernment of all theſe Kingdomes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> the great <hi>Mogor,</hi> vnleſſe it be <hi>Narſinga,</hi> and <hi>Calicute,</hi> which haue free Princes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>Of India without Ganges.</head>
                     <p>13 <hi>INdia extra Gangem,</hi> is limited on the Weſt with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limits.</note> 
                        <hi>Bengala,</hi> and the Riuer <hi>Ganges,</hi> on the South with the maine Sea, on the Eaſt with part of <hi>China,</hi> and the Eaſt Sea, and on the North with part of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>14 The chiefe Prouinces of this part of the <hi>Indies</hi> are <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> three, <hi>Pegu, Siam,</hi> and <hi>Chauchin china.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>15 In <hi>Pegu</hi> there are moſt beautifull Parrats, and great <note place="margin">Pegu.</note> ſtore of ciuet Cats. The chiefe city is <hi>Pegu.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>16 In <hi>Siam</hi> there are many Schooles, the inhabitants <note place="margin">Siam.</note> whereof are great Idolaters, worſhipping the higher Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And when any one dyeth with them, they will not bury them in the earth, but hang them vp in the aire, rather wiſhing the Birdes which are heauenly, to eate them, then the worms which are earthly to touch them. In this Prouince is alſo <hi>Comboia,</hi> the people of which do thinke themſelues and all other men to bee of the ſame nature that brute beaſts are. <hi>Hondius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18337:33"/>
                     <p> 17 In <hi>Chauchinchina,</hi> there is great ſtore of gold, ſiluer, and Purceline, of which the Purceline diſhes are made. <note place="margin">Chauchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china.</note> The inhabitants in many places of this countrey, are <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropophagi,</hi> or men eaters.</p>
                     <p>18 This part of the <hi>Indies</hi> was once gouerned by the King of <hi>Paga,</hi> and <hi>Siam,</hi> but now is brought in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> vnto one ſole King, who is King of <hi>Barma,</hi> keeping his Court in the Citie of <hi>Odia,</hi> in which are contained 200000. Citizens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>OF CHINA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>CHina</hi> is bounded on the Weſt with <hi>India,</hi> and the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Cautan,</hi> on the South with <hi>Chauchinchina,</hi> on <note place="margin">Limits.</note> the Eaſt with the Eaſt Ocean, and on the North with a wall of 600. miles in length, which defends it from the inuaſion of the <hi>Tartares.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 This Kingdome is not onely held to bee the chiefe of all <hi>Aſia,</hi> but of al the world, being ſo fertil, that it doth <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> both yeeld what is fitting for humane life, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the delicate and effeminate appetite of man may luſt after.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The inhabitants of it are very witty, politicke, great <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> Mathematicians, conceiuing ſo well of themſelues, that they are accuſtomed to ſay, that themſelues haue two eies, the people of <hi>Europe</hi> one, &amp; the reſidue of the other Nations none.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 Vnder this great kingdome are comprehended 15. Prouinces, the leaſt of which exceeds in largeneſſe the greateſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> and in them are contained 70. Kinges, which are all ſubiect vnto the King of <hi>China.</hi> The inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants are ſo many alſo, that they exceede the number of 70000000. And the cities and townes ſtand ſo thicke, that the whole kingdome ſeemeth as one mighty citie.</p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:18337:33"/>
                     <p n="5"> 5 The chiefe thinges which are to bee obſerued, in theſe Prouinces, are firſt, that there are ſome of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants which dwell in houſes vpon the Sea, buying, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and keeping market as they doe in any towne. And in many plaines they haue houſes running vpon wheels, with ſayles at the top of them, that when they will go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any place, they tarry onely for a winde to driue them. There is alſo in this Kingdome the great City of <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zay,</hi> whoſe circuit is 100. miles, hauing in it 1600000. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and 12000. ſtone bridges, among which there are ſome ſo high, that a great Shippe with top-ſaile may paſſe vnder them. In the middle of this Citie, there is a Lake thirtie miles in compaſſe, in which there are two goodly Ilands. Some put this Citie in <hi>Tartarie,</hi> ſome in <hi>China,</hi> others in the confines of both: but whereſoeuer it is, it is much ruinated ſince the time of <hi>Paulus Venetius,</hi> who maketh a full deſcription of it.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 This great kingdome is gouerned by one ſole king, <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> who is called of his ſubiects the Lord of the world, &amp; the ſonne of the ſhining Sunne.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>Of the Ilands in Aſia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus farre haue I raſhly run ouer the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent of <hi>Aſia:</hi> now therefore will I linke vnto it the deſcription of the Ilands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto.</p>
                  <p>1 The <hi>Aſian</hi> Ilands are diuided into thoſe in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, and thoſe which are in the <hi>Indian</hi> Ocean.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="region">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18337:34"/>
                  <head>Of the Ilands in the Mediterranean Sea.</head>
                  <p>2 THe chiefe Ilands in the <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> two, <hi>Rodes,</hi> and <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3 The Iland <hi>Rodes</hi> is very famous for many things, <note place="margin">Rodes.</note> but chiefly for three: The firſt is, that the Sunne was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo maskt with a cloud, but that once in a day ſhee did ſhine vpon this Iland. The ſecond is, that the great piller of the Sunne offered by the Gentiles vnto <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſtood in this Ile, made in the forme of a mighty huge man. The third &amp; laſt is, that the order of the Knights of the Rodes was held in this place.</p>
                  <p>13 The Iland <hi>Cyprus</hi> is very fuitfull, but little fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. <note place="margin">Cyprus.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>De Inſulis In Mari Indico.</head>
                  <p>5 THe chiefe Ilands in the <hi>Indian Ocean,</hi> are <hi>Ormus,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
                     <hi>Zeilan, Samatra, Aureae Iuſulae, Borneo, Iaua Maior, Iaua Minor, Iapan,</hi> the <hi>Molucco,</hi> and the <hi>Philippian I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6 <hi>Ormus</hi> is of it ſelfe a kingdome, and commaundeth <note place="margin">Ormus.</note> moſt part of the Perſian gulfe: it is exceeding barren, but the Citie <hi>Ormus</hi> (in which the Portugals doe hold a ſtrong Caſtle) is ſo faire and full of trade, that they ſay there, if the world were a ring, <hi>Ormus</hi> ought to bee the ſtone thereof.</p>
                  <p>7 The Ile <hi>Zeilan</hi> is ſeated in <hi>Sinus Bengala,</hi> in which <note place="margin">Zeilan.</note> there are Fieldes whoſe graſſe continually groweth, and Trees that are laden with fruit all the yeare long. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that ſome did thinke, that this was the place where <hi>Paradiſe</hi> ſtood. This Iland is ſubiect vnto the <hi>Mogor,</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>Portugalls</hi> doe hold a ſtrong Caſtle in it.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:18337:34"/>
                  <p> 8 The Iland <hi>Samatra</hi> lyeth directly vnder the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Samatra.</note> hauing in it a Fountaine which ſendeth foorth water, that if it bee put into fire, doth not quench it, but makes it burne more vehemently. In it is alſo a Mountaine which ſendeth foorth continuall flames of fire. The inhabitants of this Iland are <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>9 In <hi>Iaua Maior,</hi> the inhabitants are excellent Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <note place="margin">Iaua Maior</note> great Pirats, which acknowledge <hi>Mahumet,</hi> and liue vpon Cats and Miſe. Yet this Iland for the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie fruitfulneſſe of it, was called by <hi>Scaliger,</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium</hi> of the world.</p>
                  <p>10 In <hi>Iaua Minor</hi> little is worth the noting, onely that <note place="margin">Iaua Minor</note> it doth flouriſh with Spices.</p>
                  <p>11 In the Iland <hi>Iapan,</hi> the inhabitants are very ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, <note place="margin">Iapan.</note> and great Idolaters, waſhing their children ſo ſoone as they bee borne in Riuers. They will neuer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo come into the roomes where they dine or eate any thing, with their ſhooes on their feete, but keepe the places (as they tearme it) hallowed. This Iland hath very much golde in it, inſomuch that <hi>Paule Venetus</hi> doth affirme, that in his time the Kings Palace was couered with gold.</p>
                  <p>12 The <hi>Moluccoe Ilands</hi> are famous for the great <note place="margin">Moluccoes</note> plenty of ſpices which are in them. There is alſo in theſe Iſles a Bird, called <hi>Monicodiata,</hi> which hath no feete, continually flying without intermiſsion. The female of this Bird doth lay her egges when ſhee breedes in a hole which is in the backe of the Male, like vnto a neſt, &amp; theſe are neuer taken before they dye and fall vpon the earth.</p>
                  <p>The inhabitants of theſe Ilands go naked, and are great Idolaters.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18337:35"/>
                  <p> 13 The <hi>Philippian Ilands</hi> lye North of the <hi>Moluccoes,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Philippians</note> the ayre being very temperate, bringeth forth all kind of Spices.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>De America, ſiue India Orientali.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing diſcourſt of three parts of the world, <hi>Europe, Africa,</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> I will now venter on the laſt &amp; greateſt part, which is <hi>America.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>America</hi> is inuironed on the Eaſt with the maine Ocean, on the South <note place="margin">Limits.</note> with the Straights of <hi>Magelane,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Mare Del Zur,</hi> or <hi>Pacificum,</hi> and on the north with the vnknowne Land.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 This part of the world, was firſt diſcried by <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus,</hi> in the yeare 1492. and then after that made better knowne by <hi>Americus Veſputius,</hi> of whome it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto this day <hi>America.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The fruitfulneſſe of this ſoyle is to be admired, for <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> in it are wonderfull ſtore of Spices, Birdes, and Fiſhes. There is alſo gold in ſuch plenty, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> haue reported they haue digged in ſome places more Golde then earth. The chiefeſt want in this part are Horſes, of which they haue few or none, and which was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> brought Horſes in the battell againſt them, they fell down aſtoniſhed, thinking that when the horſes neighed, they had ſpoken vnto them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The inhabitants of this mighty Territory, are moſt <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> barbarous, being in ſome places men eaters, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ignorant and vnlearned, which was the cheiefe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18337:35"/> cauſe that they conceited themſelues, when any one of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did read a letter, the Diuel told him the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. They are ignorant of the vſe of yron, and eſtimate glaſſe aboue gold. To conclude, they are excellent run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſwimmers.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 This fourth part of the world, is chiefly vnder the <note place="margin">Gouernment</note> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and is diuided firſt into two parts, <hi>Mexica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and <hi>Peruana,</hi> afterwards ſubdiuided as followeth.</p>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>DE MEXICANA.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 <hi>MExicana</hi> is limited on the eaſt with <hi>Mare Del Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Limits.</note> on the Weſt with <hi>Mare Del Zur,</hi> on the South with an <hi>Iſtmus,</hi> betwixt <hi>Peruana</hi> and it, and on the North with the vnknowne land.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 In this part of <hi>America</hi> are many Prouinces, the <note place="margin">Prouinces.</note> chief of which are <hi>Quiuira, Mexicana, Nicaragua, Iucatan, Florida, Virginia, Norumbega, Noua Francia, Terra Cortea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, and Eſtotiland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 The Prouince of <hi>Quiuira</hi> extendeth it ſelfe vnto <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Quiuira.</note> 
                        <hi>Califormia,</hi> being a moſt dry and barren ground.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 The Prouince of <hi>Mexicana</hi> was firſt found out by <note place="margin">Mexicana.</note> 
                        <hi>Ferdinando Corteſius,</hi> in the yeare 1518. There are in this place many Riuers, in which breede great ſtore of Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadiles, whoſe bodies the inhabitants doe eate. There are alſo many mines of golde. And there is a mountaine called <hi>Popochampeche,</hi> which doth continually vomit forth flames of fire. The chiefe and Metropolitane citie of this Prouince, or of whole <hi>America,</hi> is <hi>Mexico,</hi> in which the Prorex for <hi>Spaine</hi> doth lie, and in which there is both money coyned, and bookes printed.</p>
                     <p n="5">5 The next is <hi>Nicaragua,</hi> wherin is a great lake which <note place="margin">Nicaragua.</note> hath no entercourſe with the Sea, and yet doth ebbe &amp; flow as the Sea doth. The people in this place are more
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18337:36"/> manlike then others, both in behauiour and ſhape.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 In <hi>Iucatan Cherſoneſus,</hi> the chiefe citie is <hi>Guatimala,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Iucatan.</note> where another Vice-Roy for <hi>Spaine</hi> doth lye. The inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this Countrey did adore the Croſſe before <hi>Cortez</hi> comming.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 <hi>Terra Florida</hi> (ſo called of the French, who firſt <note place="margin">Terra Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida.</note> founded it) hath in it many Prouinces, whereof <hi>Panuca</hi> is one, in which the people are very warlike, but butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly minded, killing all the captiues they take, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them. Furthermore, they neuer marry vntil they be 40. yeares of age, and liue moſt vpon Serpents &amp; worms. There is another place in this Prouince, called <hi>Alberdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> wherin the women let their children ſucke vntil they be 12. yeares of age.</p>
                     <p n="8">8 <hi>Virginia</hi> (ſo nominated of our late Queene) was firſt <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia.</note> found out by Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> who gaue it that name. Of this Countrey what may be ſpoken more at large, ſee the diſcourſe of Maſter <hi>Harriot,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Hackant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">9 <hi>Norumbega</hi> (ſo called of certaine fiſhes which are <note place="margin">Norumbega.</note> in it of that name.) The chiefe Citie of it is <hi>Norum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bega.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10 <hi>Noua Frauncia</hi> lyeth neere vnto that great <hi>Sinus</hi> of <note place="margin">Noua Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</note> Saint <hi>Laurence.</hi> It was diſcouered and taken firſt of the French men, vnder <hi>Frauncis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Prouince haue little boats made of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which they vſe to fiſh in, &amp; when they haue done to take them vp at their backe, and carry them away.</p>
                     <p n="11">11 <hi>Terra Cortealis,</hi> is little famous, vnleſſe it be for a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">Terra Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tealis.</note> there, which is called the three brothers.</p>
                     <p n="12">12 <hi>Estotiland</hi> was firſt found out by <hi>Anthony Zenus</hi> a <note place="margin">Eſtotiland.</note> 
                        <hi>Venetian,</hi> neere vnto which lyeth <hi>Fretum Dauis,</hi> where they haue ſought oftentimes for a paſſage vnto the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luccoes</hi> &amp; <hi>China,</hi> but it could not be effected. Not far from
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18337:36"/> this lyeth <hi>Newfound-land,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence commeth moſt of our fiſh. And in the North part lyeth a land, called by Sir <hi>Frauncis Drake, Noua Albion,</hi> of which nothing can bee certainely ſpoken.</p>
                     <p n="13">13 Thus farre of the Prouinces of <hi>Mexicana,</hi> now followeth the deſcription of <hi>Peruana.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="territory">
                     <head>De Peruana.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PEruana</hi> is in euery place inuironed with the Sea, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <note place="margin">Limits.</note> it be towards the North, where it is ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Mexicana,</hi> by a little <hi>Iſtmus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2 This part of <hi>America</hi> doth chiefly flouriſh with gold, <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> pretious ſtones, Spices, Suger, &amp; ſtrange hearbs, among which is that hearbe <hi>Tobaco,</hi> which is ſo much, and idely vſed amongſt vs.</p>
                     <p>3 The inhabitants of this place are generally cruell, <note place="margin">Inuentions.</note> rude, barbarous, and men eaters, not vnlike vnto thoſe of <hi>Mexicana:</hi> They go naked, and if they take any man cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, they ſlice his body out into collops, and broile it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the coales, making mery ſo long as that indures them. They are towards the South part mighty great men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Idolaters, worſhipping the Diuell, or ſome mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous miſhapen Idole.</p>
                     <p>4 The chiefe Riuer of this Southerne part of <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Riuers.</note> are three, the Riuer <hi>Amazon, Maragon,</hi> and the golden Riuer <hi>Rio,</hi> or <hi>de la Plate,</hi> in which there is found much gold and ſiluer.</p>
                     <p>5 This <hi>Peruana</hi> is diuided into foure great Prouinces <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> or Kingdomes, <hi>Caſtella Aurea, Peru, Chile,</hi> and <hi>Braſile:</hi> In each of which the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath his Agents.</p>
                     <p>6 <hi>Caſtella Aurea,</hi> doth comprehend in it the whole <hi>Iſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Castella Aurea.</note> which doth linke and tye the two parts of <hi>America</hi> together. In it are the two famous Ports or Hauens, in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18337:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> which the Spaniſh Ships are either laden for <hi>Spaine,</hi> or disburdened for <hi>America.</hi> The one called <hi>Theomina,</hi> or <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> the other <hi>Panamais.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7 <hi>Peru</hi> is limited on the North with <hi>Caſtella Aurea,</hi> on <note place="margin">Peru.</note> the Weſt with <hi>Mare Pacificum,</hi> or the calme Sea, on the South with <hi>Chile,</hi> and on the Eaſt with a <hi>Mediterranean</hi> vnknowne. This place was found out by <hi>Frauncis Piza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> in the yeare 1525.</p>
                     <p>8 The inhabitants of this Region are great Idolaters, <note place="margin">Inhabitants.</note> worſhipping in ſome places blacke filthy ſheepe, in other places Serpents. They are alſo ſuch great men of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the Spaniards haue found teeth of them that were three fingers in breadth, and foure in length.</p>
                     <p>9 The fruitfulneſſe of this countrey doth chiefly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> in the hearbe <hi>Tobaco,</hi> and <hi>Cocam,</hi> which if it be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any mans mouth, it quencheth his thirſt. And there is a certaine Beaſt, that when hee runneth away hath a bag hanging downe vnder his belly, into which his young ones conuey themſelues. There is alſo ſuch plenty of Gold, that the inhabitants care not for it, and when the Spaniards came thither firſt, they ſhooed their Horſes with it. In this Prouince are the three riuers before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the generall deſcription of <hi>Peruana.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>10 The chiefe citie of this Kingdome is <hi>Michaelia,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Citie.</note> in which lyeth a Protex for <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>11 <hi>Chile</hi> doth flouriſh in many things, but that which <note place="margin">Chile.</note> is of greateſt note, there is a Riuer which in the day time doth runne, and in the night ſtandeth ſtill: the reaſon is, becauſe this riuer lyeth vnder Mountaines, on which ſnow falling, in the day is diſſolued, in the night congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The chiefe and Metropolitan City of this Prouince, is the citie of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> in which lyeth another Protex for <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18337:37"/>
                     <p> 12 <hi>Braſile</hi> is extended from the riuer <hi>Maragon,</hi> vnto <note place="margin">Braſile.</note> the ſtraights of <hi>Mageian.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>13 The inhabitants of this large Prouince, are <hi>ſine Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inhabitants</note> 
                        <hi>Lege, &amp; Rege:</hi> that is, without faith, law, or King. They are alſo ſuch excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſwimmers, that they can tary vnder water for the ſpace of an houre. They are very great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, ſhedding teares (which they haue alwayes in readineſſe) when any of their friends come vnto them.</p>
                     <p>14 The fruitfulneſſe of this Countrey lyeth much in <note place="margin">Qualitie.</note> Sugar, and a wood called <hi>Braſile,</hi> which is tranſported from thence into many parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> In this Country is alſo that Beaſt, called <hi>Pigritia,</hi> which in fifteene dayes will be going as farre as one can throw a ſtone. Here are alſo many ſtrange Hearbes, whereof two are of moſt note. The firſt is the hearbe <hi>Copaibas,</hi> of which the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Balſomum</hi> is made, that cureth all greene wounds. The other is an hearbe, which of the Portugals is called <hi>Sentida,</hi> of <hi>Lincotanus Sentiens,</hi> and of others <hi>Viua,</hi> whoſe qualitie is, that if any one throw any thing vnto it, or touch it, it will ſhut his leaues, and will not open them vntill the partie which did diſpleaſe it be departed Here are alſo neere vnto the Sea-ſhore, Fiſhes which will flye like vnto birds. And to conclude, here are trees of that bigneſſe, that there are as many families dwelling in one of the limbs of them, as are in ſome Pariſhes of England. <hi>Magin.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:18337:38"/>
               <head>CAP. X.</head>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>De America Inſulis.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus farre of the continent and Kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in <hi>America:</hi> Now onely remaines the deſcription of ſome few and particu-Ilands, and then I haue finiſhed what in fine I wiſhed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The Ilands of <hi>America</hi> are diuided into thoſe which <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> are in <hi>Mari Del Nort,</hi> and thoſe in <hi>Mari del Zur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The knowne Ilands in <hi>Mari Del Nort,</hi> are fiue, <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaniola, Iamaica, Cuba, Caribum, and Cimbubon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 In the Iland <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> there are many mynes of <note place="margin">Hiſpaniola.</note> Golde. The chiefe Citie in it, is Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> in which the Archbiſhop therof doth continually lye. This was the Iland which <hi>Columbus</hi> did firſt finde out.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 In <hi>Iamaica,</hi> or the Iland of <hi>Saint Iames,</hi> little is to be <note place="margin">Iamaica.</note> obſerued, onely that in it there is a Citie called Siuill, in which there is a faire Abby.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 In the Iland <hi>Cuba,</hi> the Metropolitan Citie is <hi>Haua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cuba.</note> ſo called, becauſe it is the Hauen where all the Ships doe ſuccour themſelues, which come from <hi>Spaine</hi> vnto <hi>Peru,</hi> or the contrary.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 In the Iland <hi>Caribum,</hi> the inhabitants are all <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropophagi:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Caribum.</note> And from hence is brought that woade which is called <hi>Guaicum, or Lignum Sanctum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7 In the <hi>Iland Cimbubon,</hi> there is a Tree very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <note place="margin">Cimbubon.</note> for his leaues, which when they fall vnto the earth, doe creepe, hauing on either ſide thinges like
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18337:38"/> vnto two feete, beſides, if one offer to touch or come neere vnto them, they will moue, and offer to run away. <hi>Guilandinus</hi> reporteth it, and <hi>Scaliger</hi> in his 112. exerciſe againſt <hi>Cardanus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="region">
                  <head>De Inſulis in Mari Del Zur.</head>
                  <p>1 IN <hi>Mari Del Zur,</hi> there are onely three Ilands which <note place="margin">Haccari.</note> are knowne, called <hi>Hacari,</hi> in which are great ſtore of Golde.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>Quem nos depictum vix recte aſpeximus orbem,</l>
                        <l>Solius verbi fabrica ſola fuit.</l>
                        <l>Illi igitur terrae qui fundamenta locauit,</l>
                        <l>Sit ſoli noſtro gloria ſola Deo.</l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:39"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>1 AFrica.</item>
               <item>2 America.</item>
               <item>3 Aſia.</item>
               <item>4 Arabia.</item>
               <item>5 Abiſsinorum Regio.</item>
               <item>6 Armenia.</item>
               <item>7 Azores Inſulae.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>1 Barbaria.</item>
               <item>2 Braſilia.</item>
               <item>3 Baliares Inſulae.</item>
               <item>4 Belgia.</item>
               <item>5 Britania Magna.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>1 China.</item>
               <item>2 Corſica.</item>
               <item>3 Candia.</item>
               <item>4 Cyprus</item>
               <item>5 Chile.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>1 Dania.</item>
               <item>2 Dacia Vetus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>1 Europea.</item>
               <item>2 Egypt.</item>
               <item>3 Ethiopia Inferior.</item>
               <item>4 Eſtotilandia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>1 Friſlandia Inſulae.</item>
               <item>2 Florida.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>1 Gallia.</item>
               <item>2 Germania.</item>
               <item>Grecia.</item>
               <item>Groinlandia.</item>
               <item>Groclandia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>1 Hiſpania.</item>
               <item>2 Hungaria.</item>
               <item>3 Hibernia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>1 Italia.</item>
               <item>2 Illiria.</item>
               <item>3 India.</item>
               <item>4 Iſlandia.</item>
               <item>5 Inſulae in Mari Atlant.</item>
               <item>6 Inſulae in Mar. Egeo.</item>
               <item>7 Inſulae in Mar. Ethiopico.</item>
               <item>8 Inſulae in Mar. Indico.</item>
               <item>9 Inſulae in Mar. Del Nort.</item>
               <item>10 Inſulae in Mar. Del Zur.</item>
               <item>11 Iſchia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>1 Lituania.</item>
               <item>2 Liuonia.</item>
               <item>3 Libia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>1 Moſcouia.</item>
               <item>2 Mexicana.</item>
               <item>3 Malta.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>1 Nigretarum Regio.</item>
               <item>2 Numidia.</item>
               <item>3 Noruegia.</item>
               <item>4 Natolia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>1 Ormus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>1 Polonia.</item>
               <item>2 Pruſsia.</item>
               <item>3 Perſia.</item>
               <item>4 Peruana.</item>
               <item>5 Peru.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18337:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item> 6 Paleſtina.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>1 Rodes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>1 Scandia.</item>
               <item>2 Scicilia.</item>
               <item>3 Sardinia.</item>
               <item>4 Sweuia.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>1 Tartaria.</item>
               <item>2 Tranſiluania.</item>
               <item>3 Turcicurh Imperium Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropeum.</item>
               <item>4 Turcia Aſiana.</item>
               <item>5 Terra Borealis Incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita.</item>
               <item>6 Terra Auſtralis Incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>1 Virginia.</item>
               <item>2 Venice.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z</head>
               <item>1 Zazinthus.</item>
               <item>2 Zeilan.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_longitudes_and_latitudes">
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Table of the chiefe Cities contained in the whole world,</hi> with their Longitudes and Latitudes anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed <hi>thereunto.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</cell>
                     <cell>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</cell>
                     <cell>lat.</cell>
                     <cell>lat.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>D.</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell>D.</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>ALexandria in Egypt.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Amſterdam in Belgia.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Antuerpe in Belgia.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Angiers in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Argentine in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Athens in Greece.</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Belgia in Chaldea.</cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Bethlem in Iudea.</cell>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Bengala in Indies.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Biſancon in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Bourges in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Buda in Hugarie.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Caliz in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Calicute in Indies.</cell>
                     <cell>112</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Coimbra in Portugall.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Conſtantinople in Greece.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Colen in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Copenhagen in Denmarke.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>Compoſtella in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>Corinth in Greece.</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>Cracouia in Polonia.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Damaſcus in Iudea.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Doway in Belgia.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Edenburge in Scotland.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Epheſus in Natolia.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18337:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>F.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Florence in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Frankfort ad Maenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Germany</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Frankfort ad oder. Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Geneua in Sauoy.</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Goa in Indies.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Granado in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Ieruſalem in Iudea.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Ingolſtad.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Lacedemon in Natolia.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Leiden in Belgia.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Lisbon in Portugal.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Louaine in ſtelgia.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>London in England.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Luteſia in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>Lions in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Ments in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Mexico in America.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Millaine in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Moſcouia in Ruſsia.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>N</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Naples in Italy,</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Nice in Natolia.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Niniuie in Aſiria.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Nidroſia in Noruegia.</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Orleance in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Ormus in the Ile Ormus.</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Oxford in England.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Paris in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Padua in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Pauia in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18337:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Poicters in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Prage in Bohemia.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Rome in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Rodes in the Ile Rodes.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Riga in Lyuonia.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Siuill in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Siracuſa in Scicilie,</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Sienna in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Stockholme in Sweuia.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Saint Iago in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Tarſus in Natolia.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Tolledo in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Tollouſe in Fraunce.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>Triers in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Valentia in Spaine.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Venice in Italy.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>Vienna in Auſtria.</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Witteberge in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>Witsberge in Germany.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18337:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
